<TEXT><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Shad</ENAMEX> said he wanted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> to write a better definition of insider trading but thought action should wait until the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Supreme Court</ENAMEX> ruled on an insider trading case. Id like the benefit of the Winans decision before deciding on a definition, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shad</ENAMEX> told a Senate Appropriations subcommittee hearing. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shad</ENAMEX> was refering to the appeal by former <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wall Street Journal</ENAMEX> reporter <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">R. Foster Winans</ENAMEX> of his conviction on insider trading charges for telling a friend in advance what stocks he was going to write about in his column. The stocks usually went up or down in price depending on Winans recommendation. He said insider trading accounted for only 11 percent of the SECs enforcement activities last year despite the publicity given to recent major cases. Insider trading makes up only a tiny fraction of one pct of the 50 billion dlrs of daily securities trading, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shad</ENAMEX> said. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shad</ENAMEX> asked for a budget increase so the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">SEC</ENAMEX> could enlarge its enforcement staff by 20 this year and 73 next year to deal with all types of securities fraud. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Shad</ENAMEX> said he hoped to start his new duties as U.S. Ambassador to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX> by June. He said he did not know when his successor would be named by President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX>. </TEXT>