<TEXT><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Investment Canada</ENAMEX> said it has allowed the indirect takeover of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Holt, Rinehart and Winston Canada Ltd.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">W.B. Saunders Co of Canada Ltd.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Les Editions HRW Ltd.</ENAMEX> by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harcourt Brace Jovanovich Canada Inc.</ENAMEX> The government agency said, however, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harcourt Canada</ENAMEX> has agreed to sell control of the firms to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canadian</ENAMEX> interests within two years. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Harcourt</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canadas U.S.</ENAMEX> parent, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Harcourt Brace Jovanovich Inc.</ENAMEX> HBJ, indirectly acquired the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canadian</ENAMEX> book publishing companies when it purchased <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Holt Rinehart and Winston</ENAMEX> from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CBS Inc.</ENAMEX> CBS last October. </TEXT>