<TEXT>A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> official said there are no plans to try to reduce the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> budget deficit by issuing yen-denominated bonds that would become known as <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX> bonds. It simply isnt something that we are planning to do, the official said. He added the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> was aware of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japanese</ENAMEX> news reports suggesting the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX> administration might issue such bonds as the former <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carter</ENAMEX> administration did when it sold <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carter</ENAMEX> bonds denominated in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West German</ENAMEX> marks. But he said the situation was greatly different now. If you look at the differences between the treasury market now and in the Carter administration years, it is a much more global market now, the official said. There was not the same ease then for the holder of another currency to buy other countries securities, he added, But there is no difficulty now for them to purchase dollars and buy <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> securities. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> needs dollars, not <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japanese</ENAMEX> yen, to pay its debts and reduce the deficit and so has no plans to issue yen-denominated bonds, he emphasized. </TEXT>