<TEXT>Cheap oil feedstocks, the weakened <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> dollar and a plant utilization rate approaching 90 pct will propel the streamlined <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> petrochemical industry to record profits this year, with growth expected through at least 1990, major company executives predicted. This bullish outlook for chemical manufacturing and an industrywide move to shed unrelated businesses has prompted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GAF Corp</ENAMEX>, privately-held <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cain Chemical Inc.</ENAMEX>, and other firms to aggressively seek acquisitions of petrochemical plants. Oil companies such as <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashland Oil Inc.</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Kentucky</ENAMEX>-based oil refiner and marketer, are also shopping for money-making petrochemical businesses to buy. I see us poised at the threshold of a golden period, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Paul Oreffice</ENAMEX>, chairman of giant <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow Chemical Co.</ENAMEX> Theres no major plant capacity being added around the world now. The whole game is bringing out new products and improving the old ones. Analysts say the chemical industrys biggest customers, automobile manufacturers and home builders that use a lot of paints and plastics, are expected to buy quantities this year. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> petrochemical plants are currently operating at about 90 pct capacity, reflecting tighter supply that could hike product prices by 30 to 40 pct this year, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Dosher</ENAMEX>, managing director of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pace Consultants Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX>. Demand for some products such as styrene could push profit margins up by as much as 300 pct, he said. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Oreffice</ENAMEX>, speaking at a meeting of chemical engineers in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> would easily top the 741 mln dlrs it earned last year and predicted it would have the best year in its history. In 1985, when oil prices were still above 25 dlrs a barrel and chemical exports were adversely affected by the strong <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> dollar, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dow</ENAMEX> had profits of 58 mln dlrs. I believe the entire chemical industry is headed for a record year or close to it, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Oreffice</ENAMEX> said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GAF</ENAMEX> chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Samuel Heyman</ENAMEX> estimated that the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> chemical industry would report a 20 pct gain in profits during 1987. Last year, the domestic industry earned a total of 13 billion dlrs, a 54 pct leap from 1985. The turn in the fortunes of the once-sickly chemical industry has been brought about by a combination of luck and planning, said Paces <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Dosher</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dosher</ENAMEX> said last years fall in oil prices made feedstocks dramatically cheaper and at the same time the American dollar was weakening against foreign currencies. That helped boost <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> chemical exports. Also helping to bring supply and demand into balance has been the gradual market absorption of the extra chemical manufacturing capacity created by Middle Eastern oil producers in the early 1980s. Finally, virtually all major <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> chemical manufacturers have embarked on an extensive corporate restructuring program to mothball inefficient plants, trim the payroll and eliminate unrelated businesses. The restructuring touched off a flurry of friendly and hostile takeover attempts. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GAF</ENAMEX>, which made an unsuccessful attempt in 1985 to acquire <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Union Carbide Corp.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">UK</ENAMEX>, recently offered three billion dlrs for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Borg Warner Corp.</ENAMEX> BOR, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> manufacturer of plastics and chemicals. Another industry powerhouse, W.R. Grace GRA has divested its retailing, restaurant and fertilizer businesses to raise cash for chemical acquisitions. But some experts worry that the chemical industry may be headed for trouble if companies continue turning their back on the manufacturing of staple petrochemical commodities, such as ethylene, in favor of more profitable specialty chemicals that are custom-designed for a small group of buyers. Companies like <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">DuPont</ENAMEX> DD and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Monsanto Co</ENAMEX> MTC spent the past two or three years trying to get out of the commodity chemical business in reaction to how badly the market had deteriorated, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dosher</ENAMEX> said. But I think they will eventually kill the margins on the profitable chemicals in the niche market. Some top chemical executives share the concern. The challenge for our industry is to keep from getting carried away and repeating past mistakes, GAFs <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Heyman</ENAMEX> cautioned. The shift from commodity chemicals may be ill-advised. Specialty businesses do not stay special long. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cain Chemical</ENAMEX>, created this month by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sterling investment banking group</ENAMEX>, believes it can generate 700 mln dlrs in annual sales by bucking the industry trend. Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gordon Cain</ENAMEX>, who previously led a leveraged buyout of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Duponts Conoco Incs</ENAMEX> chemical business, has spent 1.1 billion dlrs since January to buy seven petrochemical plants along the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Texas Gulf Coast</ENAMEX>. The plants produce only basic commodity petrochemicals that are the building blocks of specialty products. This kind of commodity chemical business will never be a glamorous, high-margin business, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cain</ENAMEX> said, adding that demand is expected to grow by about three pct annually. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Garo Armen</ENAMEX>, an analyst with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dean Witter Reynolds</ENAMEX>, said chemical makers have also benefitted by increasing demand for plastics as prices become more competitive with aluminum, wood and steel products. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Armen</ENAMEX> estimated the upturn in the chemical business could last as long as four or five years, provided the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> economy continues its modest rate of growth. </TEXT>