<TEXT>Storage problems with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brazils</ENAMEX> record grain crop are likely to result in losses of about five mln tonnes, an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Agriculture Ministry</ENAMEX> spokesman said. Ministry spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Leonardo Brito</ENAMEX>, speaking from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brasilia</ENAMEX>, told <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX> he believed that about five mln tonnes of this years estimated crop of 65 mln tonnes would be lost. He said part of this would be the normal loss inevitable in harvesting, but that most of it would stem from storage problems. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brazil</ENAMEX> has a storage capacity of 66 mln tonnes, theoretically sufficient for the crop. But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brito</ENAMEX> said that the storage capacity was badly distributed. The states of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sao Paulo</ENAMEX>,<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Parana</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Rio Grande do Sul</ENAMEX> had between them 70 pct of the nations capacity, but were responsible for only 50 to 60 pct of production. The biggest problems are concentrated in the Centre-West growing regions, where rising production has outpaced storage capacity. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brito</ENAMEX> said the Centre-West, whose crops include soya and maize, had between 30 and 40 pct of the nations grains production but only 20 pct of its storage space. In addition to the poor distribution of storage units, there is the problem that too much of the capacity is geared to storing grain in sacks, while not enough is suitable for storing loose grain, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brito</ENAMEX> said. Finally, there is a shortage of lorries to transport the crops. The sheer scale of the task in transporting the record crop has been evident from television reports, which have shown enormous queues of lorries waiting outside granaries. </TEXT>