<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960108.0493 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A5852 </STORYID>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-08</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0745 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">England</ENAMEX>, and an Irish balloonist, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rory McCarthy</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Branson</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lindstrand</ENAMEX>, who have set several ballooning records,
were the first pilots of hot-air balloons to cross both the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic Ocean</ENAMEX>, in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1987</TIMEX>, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pacific</ENAMEX>, in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lindstrand</ENAMEX> said that because of unfavorable weather patterns
over <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">England</ENAMEX> he and his colleagues had decided to launch their
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Virgin</ENAMEX> Global Challenger from a military airfield at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Marrakech</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Morocco</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   To move the big crew capsule, balloon and accessories, the
British group chartered a Beluga transport plane  &MD;  a modified
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Airbus</ENAMEX> 300 similar to the Pregnant Guppy aircraft used by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NASA</ENAMEX> to
transport large rocket components. The flight to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Morocco</ENAMEX> is
scheduled for <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Friday</TIMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lindstrand</ENAMEX> said the balloon launching
would probably take place <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">a day or so later</TIMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Branson</ENAMEX>, chairman of the multifaceted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Virgin Group</ENAMEX>, which
includes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Virgin Atlantic Airways</ENAMEX>, believes that his competitor,
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fossett</ENAMEX>, faces grave risks.
<p>
   ``Because his capsule is not pressurized,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Branson</ENAMEX> said in an
interview, ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve</ENAMEX> will have to stay at around 20,000 feet, which
is usually well below the core of the jet stream. That could slow
him down a lot. We will be at 30,000 to 35,000 feet, where our
chances of riding the high-speed jet stream are much better.
<p>
   ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve</ENAMEX> is incredibly brave, and if anyone should beat us, I'd
rather it was he.''
<p>
   The Dutch team, led by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Henk Brink</ENAMEX>, recently tested the inflation
of its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unicef</ENAMEX> Flyer balloon at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cape Kennedy</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NASA</ENAMEX>'s huge Vehicle
Assembly Building, where space shuttles are prepared for flight.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brink</ENAMEX>, who intends to launch his balloon from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nijmegen</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">the
Netherlands</ENAMEX>, is a helicopter instructor and veteran balloonist.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1986</TIMEX>, he, his wife, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Evelien</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Hageman</ENAMEX>, a Dutch
fighter pilot, became the first European balloonists to cross the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic</ENAMEX>; so precise was their navigation that they landed within a
few miles of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brink</ENAMEX>'s home in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">the Netherlands</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Although balloons must travel in the same direction as the wind
that carries them along, a pilot can navigate to some extent by
changing altitude to seek wind headed in the desired direction.
Even a small change in altitude can result in a large change in
direction.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Unicef</ENAMEX> Flyer flight suffered a setback <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Dec. 26</TIMEX> when its
third crew member, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wouter Bakker</ENAMEX>, resigned from the flight crew
``for personal reasons.''
<p>
   Days before the expected launching <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this week</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brink</ENAMEX> said in an
interview that he had advertised for a replacement, stipulating
that the third crew member should be an airline captain.
<p>
   ``We're down to three candidates,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brink</ENAMEX> said <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Friday</TIMEX>, ``and all
of them are completely familiar with our navigation and
communication equipment. For the launch and landing, I will do the
piloting.''
<p>
   All three teams are flying Rozier balloons  &MD;  a type that has
achieved many long-distance records in recent years.
<p>
   A modern Rozier is kept aloft by helium gas, but to add extra
lift, the balloon is compartmentalized and the lower part can be
filled with hot air from a gas burner. This enables the balloon to
maintain altitude at night, when cold air and the lack of sunlight
cools the helium and lessens its lifting power.
<p>
as too dangerous.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-08-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1751EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960131.0611 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A9510 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">HILL</ENAMEX>-OBIT-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-31</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">HILL</ENAMEX>-OBIT-NYT
(<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Del.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mo.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX> ATTN)
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">JULIAN HILL</ENAMEX>, 91, WHO DISCOVERED NYLON
(lb)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">DAVID STOUT</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Julian Hill</ENAMEX>, a research chemist whose accidental discovery of a
tough, taffylike compound revolutionized everyday life after it
proved its worth in warfare and courtship, died on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Sunday</TIMEX> in
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hockessin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Del.</ENAMEX> He was 91.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> died at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cokesbury Village</ENAMEX> retirement community, where
he had lived in recent years with his wife of <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">62 years</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Polly</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   During <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">the late 1920s</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> was a member of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du Pont Co.</ENAMEX> team
studying the behavior of certain molecules that chain together to
form larger ones, called polymers. The chemists were engaged in
pure research, though finding a substitute for silk was in the back
of their minds.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1930</TIMEX>, while trying to create ever larger structures by
adjusting the amount of water in a batch of carbon- and
alcohol-based molecules, the team came up with a concoction that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du
Pont</ENAMEX>'s research head, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wallace Carothers</ENAMEX>, thought useless.
<p>
   But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> was intrigued after sticking a heated glass rod into a
beaker containing the material and finding that it stretched and
pulled, like taffy, and that it became silky when stretched at room
temperature. Soon, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> and his colleagues were playing with the
material in the corridor and finding that it could be shaped into
strands that were remarkably long and strong.
<p>
   The substance, of course, was nylon, although it would not be so
named until it was introduced at the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1939</TIMEX> World's Fair in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>
 &MD;  hence, the ``ny'' in nylon.
<p>
   ``I tell my wife I was something better than a good scientist,''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> recalled in an interview years later. ``I was lucky.'' Since
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du Pont</ENAMEX> held the patents to nylon, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> made no great fortune off
the discovery, but his wife said <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> that the company had
treated him well over the years.
<p>
   (A sad footnote is the fate of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carothers</ENAMEX>. Beset by personal
problems that fueled depression, thinking himself a failure despite
a brilliant career, he committed suicide in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1937</TIMEX> at the age of 41.)
<p>
   If the development of nylon was in part serendipity, it was not
a total surprise. Almost a <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">decade earlier</TIMEX>, at an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Chemical
Society</ENAMEX> conference in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Buffalo</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carothers</ENAMEX> reported on
progress in developing ``artificial silks'' like rayon, which was
then coming into use.
<p>
   But rayon is derived from cellulose and in that sense is not
strictly synthetic, as is nylon. Nylon was used initially for
toothbrush bristles, fishing line and surgical sutures. Nylon
stockings were first sold in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1939</TIMEX>. They cost twice what silk
stockings did, and women were happy to pay. Nylon stockings were
sheer and strong.
<p>
   The material was deemed so important that its use was restricted
to the military after the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> entered World War II. Nylon
was used to make rope, tents, aircraft tires and parachutes.
<p>
   It also served to improve British-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> relations, in a way.
Young American soldiers stationed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> made a good impression
on their dates by giving them nylon stockings, available from the
military's post exchanges when they could not be bought elsewhere.
<p>
   The reintroduction of nylon to civilian life after the war
caused a sensation, and at least one stampede. A crowd of 10,000
people jammed a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> department store in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1945</TIMEX>, causing the
nylon sale to be called off.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE" MIN="decades">the decades since</TIMEX>, nylon has become ubiquitous, as carpeting
and clothing. And about two-thirds of all the luggage manufactured
in the world is made from it.
<p>
   Scientists consider nylon a benign product of technology,
because it has not been found to have any deadly side effects. But
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX>, who loved wildlife and was a dedicated bird-watcher, said in
a <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1988</TIMEX> interview that he thought ``the human race is going to
perish by being smothered in plastic.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Julian Werner Hill</ENAMEX> was born in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Louis</ENAMEX>, graduated from
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Washington University</ENAMEX> there in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1924</TIMEX> and earned a doctorate in
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1928</TIMEX>. His wife recalled on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> that his doctoral studies were
delayed a year because he was stricken with scarlet fever.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> played the violin and was an accomplished squash player and
figure-skater until <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">his early 40s</TIMEX>, when an attack of polio weakened
one leg, his wife said.
<p>
   Before his retirement from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du Pont</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1964</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> supervised the
company's program of aid to universities for research in physics
and chemistry.
<p>
   Surviving besides his wife are a daughter, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Louisa Spottswood</ENAMEX> of
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Philadelphia</ENAMEX>; two sons, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joseph</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Villanova</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jefferson</ENAMEX>,
of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, and five grandchildren.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-31-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1910EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960207.0657 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=f pri=r> A6958 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tia-z> BC-DOMINICAN-AIR-CRASH-U </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-07</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0674 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-DOMINICAN-AIR-CRASH-UPDATE2-BLOOM
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BOEING</ENAMEX> AIRLINER CRASHES IN <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CARIBBEAN</ENAMEX> WITH 189 ABOARD (UPDATE2)
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Molinski</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bloomberg Business News</ENAMEX>
   (Updates with latest body total, no survivors found; adds that
search was called off for <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">the night</TIMEX>, with in second and third
paragraphs; adds report that lightning stuck the craft, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION" MIN="Foreign Ministry">German
Foreign Ministry</ENAMEX> comment response, in seventh paragraph.)
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santo Domingo</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>, <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 7</TIMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bloomberg</ENAMEX>) -- A
chartered <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 carrying German tourists from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican
Republic</ENAMEX> crashed into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION" MIN="Caribbean">Caribbean sea</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">last night</TIMEX>, leaving no sign
that any of the 189 people on board survived.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Coast Guard</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> said it recovered 79 bodies in the
area of the crash, before suspending its search at <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">nightfall</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">today</TIMEX>.
It plans to continue the search in the <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">morning</TIMEX>.
<p>
   ``We'll continue searching until there is reason to believe
there are no survivors,'' said Petty Officer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Scott Carr</ENAMEX>, a
spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coast Guard</ENAMEX>, <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">this evening</TIMEX>. ``We still maintain
hope that somebody is out there and we will try to find them.''
<p>
   Searchers did find some life rafts, but no survivors, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coast
Guard</ENAMEX> said. It wasn't clear whether the rafts were dragged out by
survivors or if they inflated on impact.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> officials said the cause of the
crash was unknown. The owner of the German tour agency that
chartered the plane was quoted by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX> as saying lightning
struck the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX>-bound 757.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vural Oeger</ENAMEX>, head of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hamburg</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oeger Tours</ENAMEX>, said he was told
by Dominican aviation officials that the plane's engines were
damaged by lightning. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX> also said the pilots apparently tried
to turn the plane around to return to the airport, but were unable
to and plunged into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   A spokeswoman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION" MIN="Foreign Ministry">German Foreign Ministry</ENAMEX> said that while
she'd heard rumors of lightning causing the wreck, she couldn't
confirm the reports.
<p>
   The plane crashed just before <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">midnight local time</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE|TIME">last night</TIMEX>,
about five minutes after taking off from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX> airport
in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coast Guard</ENAMEX> officials said rain and
sharks were hampering the rescue efforts.
<p>
   A spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing Co.</ENAMEX> said it was sending
a team to help investigate the crash.
<p>
   The aircraft, owned by Turkish company <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgen Air</ENAMEX>, was leased to
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alas de Transporte Internacional</ENAMEX>, a Dominican charter airline that
operates mainly during <TIMEX TYPE="DATE" MIN="winter">the peak winter season</TIMEX> when European
tourists visit the resort town of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX>, said a spokeswoman
for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aeronautica Civil</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>'s aviation agency.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oeger</ENAMEX> had chartered the plane from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alas</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The aircraft, built in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1985</TIMEX>, carried 176 passengers, most of
them German tourists, and 13 crew members -- 11 Turkish nationals
and two Dominicans.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Russ Young</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> spokesman, said the investigation could
last weeks or months.
<p>
   The jet was the 31st <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 made and was originally sold to
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern Air Lines</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX>, which became a subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Air
Corp.</ENAMEX> after filing for bankruptcy in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1989</TIMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Martin Brodie</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls-Royce Plc</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, said
the plane was fitted with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls-Royce</ENAMEX> RB211-535 engines. He said
the power plant was ``one of the most reliable engines in
service.''
<p>
   The company had no idea yet what went wrong and there was no
immediate evidence that the engines were to blame.
<p>
   The crash was the second of a 757 in less than <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">two months</TIMEX>. On
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Dec. 20</TIMEX>, an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines</ENAMEX> jet crashed in the mountains near
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cali</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX>, killing 160 of the 164 people on board. The cause
of that crash is still under investigation.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>, which shares the island of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hispaniola</ENAMEX>
with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Haiti</ENAMEX>, is the most popular <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX> destination for Germans.
Hundreds of thousands of German tourists visit the island each
year, attracted by its low prices and tropical beaches.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oeger</ENAMEX> is one of a number of discount tour agencies in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>
which charters planes to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-07-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2013EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960208.0062 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=i pri=u> A7267 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-DOMINICAN-CRASH-ART-2 </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-08</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0877 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-DOMINICAN-CRASH-ART-2NDLD-WRITETHRU-650&AMP;ADD-NYT
(Subs 1st graf to update number of bodies recovered)
GERMAN TOURIST PLANE CRASHES; 189 FEARED DEAD
(ART ADV: Graphic and locator-map have been sent to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NYT</ENAMEX> graphic
212-556-4204 or 1927.)
(JT)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX> 
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX> 
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 carrying 189 people, mostly tourists
on their way home to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Berlin</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican
Republic</ENAMEX>, crashed into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">late Tuesday</TIMEX> about 13 miles
offshore. At least 105 bodies were recovered, American officials
said.
<p>
   Debris was spread in an area two miles long and 150 yards wide,
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United States Coast Guard</ENAMEX> said, suggesting that the jet broke
up before it hit the water.
<p>
   But an official at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">German Embassy</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santo Domingo</ENAMEX>, the
capital of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>, said the fuel had not caught
fire, indicating that the plane had not exploded.
<p>
   The official, the first secretary at the embassy, said bad
weather was likely the cause.
<p>
   ``More than <NUMEX TYPE="PERCENT">50 percent</NUMEX>, it was the interference of bad
weather,'' the official, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Klaus D. Brock</ENAMEX>, said in a telephone
interview. The plane had taken off from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX>, about 100
miles northwest of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santo Domingo</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The crash was the second recent loss of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 in flight:
In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">December</TIMEX> a 757 crashed near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cali</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX>; pilot error appears
to have been the primary cause.
<p>
   Aviation officials in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX> gave conflicting information
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> about the flight, which reached an altitude of about
7,000 feet before crashing.
<p>
   Gen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hector Ramon</ENAMEX>, head of the civil aviation agency, said the
pilot had radioed the tower that he had a problem and was
returning, news reports said. But Maj. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Emmanuel Souffront</ENAMEX>, of the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominican Air Force</ENAMEX>, said a transcript of radio communication with
air traffic controllers indicated there had not been a problem.
<p>
   ``The aircraft started to turn to the right and disappeared from
the radar screen,'' he was quoted as saying.
<p>
   ``Before it went down, someone radioed from the aircraft, `Stand
by.'''
<p>
   In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Berlin</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX>, friends and family of the passengers
arrived at the airports to find flags flying at half staff and
teams of doctors, psychologists and clergy to meet them.
<p>
   The 11-year-old plane, originally built for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern Air Lines</ENAMEX>,
was owned by a Turkish company and under lease, with a crew, to a
Dominican airline, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alas de Transporte Internacional</ENAMEX>, for a single
flight. It carried 176 passengers, including 4 children. Eleven of
the crew were Turkish and two Dominican.
<p>
   The Turkish company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgen Air</ENAMEX>, was using the plane to fill a
charter commitment to a German company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oger Tours</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hamburg</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wolfgang Schwalm</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX> airport, said the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 had replaced a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 767 at the last minute because the
767 had technical problems.
<p>
   In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Istanbul</ENAMEX>, the general manager of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgen</ENAMEX> said on television
that he believed the plane had been hit by lightning. But the jet
is designed to withstand any such strikes.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United States Coast Guard</ENAMEX> dispatched three cutters to help
retrieve bodies. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> sent two civil aviation officials and
three officials from the federal police in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Weisbaden</ENAMEX> to help
identify bodies.
<p>
to assist investigators, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Transportation Safety
Board</ENAMEX> said it would send investigators if more evidence became
available.
<p>
   But it was not clear who would pay to retrieve the plane's data
recorder from the wreckage, off the north coast of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican
Republic</ENAMEX> where the water is about 3,000 feet deep. Retrieval could
cost <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">hundreds of thousands of dollars</NUMEX>. Though the plane was
American built, neither it nor the airline nor the flight was under
American jurisdiction, and no Americans were on board.
<p>
   Nevertheless, American safety experts said they would be very
interested in learning more about the crash if it was caused by
mechanical problems or by weather.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-08-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">0216EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960208.0763 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=i pri=u> A8248 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-DOMINICAN-CRASH-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-08</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-DOMINICAN-CRASH-NYT
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX> TO HUNT FOR BLACK BOX FROM AIR CRASH
(HLW)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">UPPER MARLBORO</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Md.</ENAMEX>  &MD;  The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said here on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> that it had
shipped equipment to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> to help find the flight
data recorder of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 that crashed offshore on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Tuesday</TIMEX>
<TIMEX TYPE="TIME">night</TIMEX>, killing all 189 people on board.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials said they had been asked to locate the so-called
black box, but so far have not been asked to help retrieve it or
any other parts of the wreckage. In the meantime, discussions
continued about who would pay to salvage parts of the jet.
<p>
   The Turkish-owned charter jet, which was leased to a Dominican
airline, was carrying German tourists home from a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX>
vacation when it plunged into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic</ENAMEX> shortly after takeoff
from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">Late on Thursday afternoon</TIMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coast Guard</ENAMEX> said
it had given up its search, and it remained uncertain exactly how
many bodies had been accounted for.
<p>
   Dominican officials said 128 bodies had been recovered. A
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> spokesman said local people in boats appeared to have
stripped some bodies of money and identification.
<p>
   After the crash, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> asked for help from the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Capt. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Raymond Scott McCord</ENAMEX>, supervisor of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>'s salvage and
diving operations, said at a briefing here on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> that the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 went down in an area where the water is from 1,000 feet
to 13,000 feet deep, with the sea bottom flat in some parts and
jagged in others.
<p>
   Although <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">McCord</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> had retrieved wreckage in more
challenging places, he declined to predict the likelihood of
success in recovering the black box in this case, or what it would
cost.
<p>
   The black boxes on passenger jets are equipped with metal
cylinders that emit a ``ping'' sound when immersed in water.
<p>
   So far, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> has sent a Towed Ping Locator System, also
known as a tow fish, to the area. The device is pulled on a cable,
about 2,500 feet above the ocean floor, at 2 to 3 knots, and,
depending on water conditions, it can hear the pinger on the black
box at a distance of up to a mile.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials and aviation experts plan to review air traffic
control radar and other data in an effort to narrow the search
area. When they finish, probably on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Tuesday</TIMEX> or <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX>, they will
begin surveying the ocean, he said.
<p>
   ``Looking for anything on the ocean floor is very difficult,
because you are working blind,'' he said. ``The analogy is a needle
in a haystack. But with a pinger locator, you know which side of
the haystack you're looking at.''
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> also showed off a bigger robot probe that would carry
out the next step, making sonar maps of the bottom, to locate the
debris fields. A third remote-controlled device, with video and
still cameras and manipulator arms, would then be sent down. All
three are towed by a ship, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> is now negotiating with
commercial ship owners for a suitable vessel, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">McCord</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   No one would say what such an operation would cost.
<p>
spokesman, said, ``any costs are expected to be incurred on a
cost-sharing basis.''
<p>
   ``We certainly have a strong interest in that aircraft; it's our
aircraft,'' he said.
<p>
   ``There are others who have an equally strong interest,'' he
said, citing ``countries and corporate entities.'' These would
apparently include <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Turkey</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alas de Transporte Internacional</ENAMEX>, which leased the plane, and
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgenair</ENAMEX>, a small Turkish company that owned the plane and
provided the crew.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-08-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2101EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960222.0661 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A3301 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">COLOMBIA</ENAMEX>-AIRCRASH-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0719 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">COLOMBIA</ENAMEX>-AIRCRASH-NYT
(EXCLUSIVE; <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">10 p.m. ET</TIMEX> EMBARGO)
JET THAT CRASHED IN <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">COLOMBIA</ENAMEX> REPORTEDLY STRIPPED OF PARTS
(HLW)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  Scavengers have descended on the wreckage of the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines</ENAMEX> jetliner that crashed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last December</TIMEX>,
making off with more than 500 parts, including the jet engines, the
landing gear, and electronic components for possible sale to other
carriers, the airline said.
<p>
   A spokesman for the airline said that to its knowledge, no parts
of the plane had yet been offered for sale, and on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Aviation Administration</ENAMEX> said it was notifying other
airlines of the possibility.
<p>
   Not long after the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 jetliner crashed <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last Dec. 20</TIMEX> in a
remote mountain area near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Buga</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX>, killing 160 of the 164
people on board, the Colombian authorities said people were taking
valuables from the bodies of the dead passengers as well as the
luggage.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Last month</TIMEX>, the airline sent other airlines and aviation
companies an 11-page list of the missing parts and their serial
numbers along with a letter warning: ``These parts could pose a
significant safety risk should they be installed on other aircraft
since they were involved in a crash.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Hotard</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX>, said by telephone: ``You
may have a part that looks perfectly good on the outside, but if
you get into some of the sophisticated testing, you may find out
it's not good.''
<p>
   Although the plane was a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757, flying from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cali</ENAMEX>,
many of the parts would also fit a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 767.
<p>
   The airline's letter, first reported in The Cleveland Plain
Dealer, noted: ``Any part taken from the crash site and/or offered
for sale without the express written approval of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines
Inc.</ENAMEX>, should be considered a stolen aircraft part.'' It cited
sections of federal law that made such activity illegal and
threatened that any supplier caught handling any of the parts would
be barred from doing business with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hotard</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX> was not interested in the salvage
value of the parts but that some could be sold for a lot of money
if passed off as being in good condition. Testifying before a
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX> aviation subcommittee <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last June</TIMEX>, federal investigators said
various small parts of airplanes that are worth <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">hundreds of dollars</NUMEX>
in new condition, are available for a <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">few dollars</NUMEX> from scrap
dealers in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> and may find their way back into
airplanes, although the parts are not suitable.
<p>
   The local Colombian authorities did retrieve the black boxes
with cockpit voice and flight data recordings, and technicians at
analyzed them. The safety board and the Colombian authorities
recently said there did not appear to be any mechanical problem
with the plane before the crash.
<p>
   That means that the stolen parts would probably not be useful in
determining the cause of this crash. In some other crashes,
investigators have sorted through tons of debris to find components
that offer clues.
<p>
   Stealing parts from crash scenes is not new. When a Colombian
DC-8 cargo plane crashed on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 5</TIMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asuncion</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paraguay</ENAMEX>, killing
23 people, local television showed a man stealing engine parts from
the debris, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">The Associated Press</ENAMEX> reported. In the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX>,
crash scenes are usually cordoned off, in part to protect the
evidence and to prevent the spread of blood-borne infection.
<p>
   A spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard F. Schleh</ENAMEX>, said the
company had helped <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX> distribute its letter, which he
described as ``a very good precautionary effort.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margaret Gilligan</ENAMEX>, the deputy associate administrator for
regulation and certification at the aviation agency, said the
agency did not believe that parts had been stolen from planes that
had crashed in this country, but she said the agency did not know
what happened abroad.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William A. Machado</ENAMEX>, who heads an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> program to investigate
aircraft parts that are counterfeit or come from unapproved
suppliers, said of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX> letter: ``It's the first time I've
seen it, but I can understand their concern, because they really
didn't have a lot of control.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Machado</ENAMEX> called the letter ``a
responsible action on their part.''
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2132EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960224.0155 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A4844 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX>-JET-CRASHES-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-24</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX>-JET-CRASHES-NYT
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX> RESTRICTS FLIGHTS OF TROUBLE-PLAGUED F-14
(kd)
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> imposed new restrictions <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Saturday</TIMEX> on
pilots who fly the F-14 jet fighter, after three of the
trouble-plagued jets crashed in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">the last month</TIMEX>, killing four <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>
airmen and three civilians.
<p>
   While the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said it had found no common thread in the recent
crashes, it announced that it had placed temporary limitations on
the speed at which F-14s could be flown, and on the use of
afterburners, which give a plane extra thrust by injecting fuel
into hot exhaust gases.
<p>
   All F-14 pilots will also be required to undergo refresher
safety courses before they are allowed to fly again, a requirement
that could keep some grounded for <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">several more days</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> made the announcement as it ended a three-day worldwide
shutdown on operations of the carrier-based F-14 Tomcat.
<p>
   In recent years the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>'s fleet of more than 330 F-14s has
suffered a series of catastrophic accidents, including a crash on
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Jan. 29</TIMEX> in which one of the early models of the fighter, an F-14A,
smashed into a residential neighborhood in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashville</ENAMEX>, killing the
two-man crew and three civilians on the ground.
<p>
   On <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 18</TIMEX>, one of the latest models, an F-14D, went down off
the coast of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION" MIN="California">southern California</ENAMEX>, killing its two-person crew.
<p>
   On <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX>, an F-14A crashed into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX>; the pilot
and radar operator survived with only minor injuries.
<p>
   The F-14 has the highest accident rate among <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> combat planes,
and its problems have mounted even as the overall safety record for
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> planes has improved dramatically in recent years. Ten F-14s
have gone down in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">the past two years</TIMEX>, and 32 since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX>. Each plane
costs more than <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$30 million</NUMEX>.
<p>
   In announcing the three-day halt to operations <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last week</TIMEX>, the
Chief of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Naval Operations</ENAMEX>, Adm. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeremy M. Boorda</ENAMEX>, said that the
F-14 was ``an airplane that we worry about.'' Earlier models of the
plane had engines that were not powerful enough for a fighter of
its size, which led to restrictions on their use and, in some
cases, replacement of the engine.
<p>
   In a statement <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Saturday</TIMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said that the new restrictions
on speed and on the use of afterburners would remain in effect
until the investigations of the three recent crashes had ended. The
statement did not rule out permanent restrictions in the future.
<p>
   ``It should be emphasized that the investigations continue to
determine causes and any permanent corrective action required,''
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said. ``The requirements and limitations placed in effect
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">today</TIMEX> are intended to permit safe operation of the F-14 aircraft
pending completion of the investigations.''
<p>
   Under the restrictions, F-14 fighters cannot fly more than 550
nautical miles an hour, below an altitude of 10,000 feet.
Restrictions on the use of afterburners apply to later models of
the plane.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials said <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Saturday</TIMEX> that the restrictions would not
affect the plane's usefulness, since the limitations would be
immediately waived in combat. ``If a pilot is out there and needs
to fly his airplane, he's going to fly his airplane as he needs
to,'' said a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> spokesman.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House National Security Committee</ENAMEX> has announced that
hearings would be held <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">next week</TIMEX> on the safety record of the F-14.
The panel is expected to hear testimony from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials, pilots
and representatives of the manufacturer, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Grumman Corp.</ENAMEX>, which
merged with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1994</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The two <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX> Republicans who are sponsoring the hearings,
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Duncan Hunter</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Randy Cunningham</ENAMEX>, both from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>, said in a
statement that ``too many lives and too much equipment has been
lost'' in F-14 crashes. Although the plane's problems precede the
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Clinton</ENAMEX> administration by many years, the lawmakers said that they
planned to investigate whether the administration ``is underfunding
both the readiness and modernization of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> aircraft.''
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-24-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1657EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960301.0672 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A1897 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-737-AIRCRASH-PROBE-NY </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">03-01</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0700 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-737-AIRCRASH-PROBE-NYT
RARE TESTING ON A 737 SEEKS ELUSIVE ANSWERS TO A CRASH
(bl)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX> 
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  Air safety investigators have begun highly unusual
tests on a parked <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 737, forcing parts askew with hydraulic
arms and clipping vital control cables in an effort to determine
why a sister plane owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USAir</ENAMEX> fell out of the sky near
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">September 1994</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The investigation of that crash, which killed all 132 people on
board, is already the most extensive in the history of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National
Transportation Safety Board</ENAMEX>. And in a way it is the most worrisome,
because the 737 is the most popular jet in the sky.
<p>
   The board finds the cause of almost all crashes by looking at
the wreckage, the flight data recorders, radar records and similar
evidence. But in this case, that has not been enough in this case.
<p>
   ``What we're doing to this airplane is unprecedented,'' said
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Hall</ENAMEX>, the safety board's chairman.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hall</ENAMEX> said investigators had already invested more than 50,000
hours of engineering time in trying to find the cause of the crash,
making the inquiry the longest and costliest in the board's <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">29-year</TIMEX>
history.
<p>
   The 737 that crashed was approaching <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> when it abruptly
rolled to the left and plunged to the ground at 300 miles an hour.
<p>
   Investigators say that its trajectory through the sky can be
explained by a sustained swing of the rudder  &MD;  the moveable surface
on the vertical tail  &MD;  and by nothing else that they can identify.
<p>
   It is not clear, though, how the rudder could have
malfunctioned.
<p>
   So technicians have pulled the floor out of the passenger cabin
of the test plane, enabling them to see the cables that link the
pedals at the pilot's feet with the rudder in the back of the
plane.
<p>
   If the cables do not snap because of the forces applied to them
during the tests, engineers will cut them and measure the sound.
The goal is to try to duplicate sounds captured by the cockpit
voice recorder just before the crash, and to see what effect a
snapped cable might have had on the plane.
<p>
   The investigators are using a plane that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USAir</ENAMEX> had removed from
service and is planning to donate to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Museum of Flight</ENAMEX>, in
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX>. The museum is across a runway from a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> plant, and
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> is assisting in the new experiments.
<p>
   The plane that crashed carried an early-model flight data
recorder, which captured only 11 kinds of data. It did not record
the position of the rudder or of the rudder controls. In contrast,
newer data recorders capture dozens of kinds of data, and usually
point investigators toward the root of the problem very quickly.
<p>
   For example, the recorder in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 that crashed off the
coast of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last month</TIMEX> had 72 kinds of data.
<p>
   Speaking by telephone from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX> as the tests began <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hall</ENAMEX> said, ``I just hope the aircraft industry and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal
Aviation Administration</ENAMEX> will take appropriate action so we are
never in a position again where it would take us this much time and
effort.''
<p>
   But the airlines argue that wiring planes to capture more data
would require taking them out of service for long periods, at high
cost.
<p>
   The plane being used for the new tests has been extensively
outfitted with instruments. ``It looks like somebody on life
support,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hall</ENAMEX>, referring to the bundles of wires that are
now attached.
<p>
   Investigators are looking for some combination of problems on
three systems that can move the plane: the main rudder-control
mechanism, a backup mechanism and a yaw damper, which is a
computer-operated automatic system that makes small adjustments in
the rudder to keep the plane's nose and tail lined up in precisely
the direction that the plane is moving.
<p>
   One reason for the new tests is that investigators say they may
not fully understand the significance of an event that occurred
just before the crash: the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USAir</ENAMEX> plane ran over the wake of a
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 737 flying 4.2 nautical miles ahead.
<p>
   Such wake encounters are common, but investigators think this
one may have put a force on the plane that somehow triggered a
fatal chain of events.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">03-01-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2134EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960301.0686 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=r> A1908 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tth-z> BC-AIRLINE-CRASHES-SPI </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">03-01</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-AIRLINE-CRASHES-SPI
LATEST CRASHES RENEW CONCERNS ABOUT AVIATION SAFETY
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients.)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">BILL VIRGIN</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Seattle Post-Intelligencer</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">SEATTLE</ENAMEX>  &MD;  Commercial aviation worldwide is off to a rocky start
in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX>, with two major crashes <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this month</TIMEX> alone claiming 312
lives.
<p>
   Other forms of transportation aren't faring much better. In the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> alone, railroad accidents have accounted for 19
deaths, 226 injuries and more than <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$62 million</NUMEX> in damage, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National
Transportation Safety Board</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Hall</ENAMEX> said <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this week</TIMEX>.
<p>
   And while crashes of airline flights get the most attention,
general aviation is usually deadlier. <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Last year</TIMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> says, 732
people died in general aviation accidents, compared with 175 deaths
from accidents involving scheduled <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> airlines. For the worst
carnage, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">America</ENAMEX>'s highways are still unrivaled, with 40,000 deaths
reported from motor vehicle accidents each year.
<p>
   Still, news of jet crashes renew questions and concerns about
aviation safety, particularly when it comes in spates and
particularly in a city like <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX>, home to the world's biggest
manufacturer of commercial jet aircraft.
<p>
   The crash of a passenger jet anywhere ``is something that
galvanizes attention,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Nance</ENAMEX>, an aviation safety expert
and writer.
<p>
   The latest crash  &MD;  that of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Faucett Airlines</ENAMEX>-operated <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>
737 in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peru</ENAMEX>, which killed 123 aboard  &MD;  came on the heels of an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX>
news conference in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this week</TIMEX> detailing its lack of success
in finding a cause for two <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> crashes of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 737s, one in
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX>, the other in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1994</TIMEX>.
<p>
   Those two crashes are linked by the remaining mystery of the
cause, the fact both involved 737s and the suspicion both crashes
may be linked to a sudden movement of the rudder, sending the
planes into uncontrollable rolls.
<p>
   But there seems to be little commonality in the three most
recent crashes, either by plane type or suspected cause. The crash
of an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">December</TIMEX>, which
killed 160 people, occurred as the plane was approaching the
airport; pilot error is suspected.
<p>
   A <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 6</TIMEX> crash of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgen Air</ENAMEX>-owned <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 occurred as the
plane was taking off from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>; that crash
claimed 189 lives. Authorities in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> say the
recorded air speed indicator at the time the plane stopped climbing
was much higher than what ground radar showed, which would suggest
pilots thought they were going faster  &MD;  and had more power to climb
 &MD;  than they actually did.
<p>
   The investigation has just begun in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peru</ENAMEX> crash, but some
witnesses say the plane was on fire before it hit the ground.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nance</ENAMEX> said there's no apparent common thread running through
those three accidents. ``The only other common denominator (would
be) the human factor, and it's been known for a long time that
human factors account for <NUMEX TYPE="PERCENT">90 percent</NUMEX> of accidents,'' he said.
``It's still the thing that gets us. We're getting better at it,
but we're not as perfect as the machines we build.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> has assisted in the investigation of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican
Republic</ENAMEX> crash and spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Russ Young</ENAMEX> said a team is being sent
to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Peru</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Until the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX> crash, the 757 hadn't been involved in any
fatal crashes in its <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">13 years</TIMEX> of flying. The 737, which in various
models has been in service for <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">28 years</TIMEX>, is the world's
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Aviation Administration</ENAMEX> hasn't issued any directives
in relation to the three most recent crashes. ``It's way too early
for that,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tim Pile</ENAMEX>. ``We would need some kind
of formal finding, unless it was really obvious there was some
problem with the aircraft.''
<p>
reported, there were 26 accidents involving scheduled aircraft,
resulting in 710 fatalities; that was down from 941 <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">the year
before</TIMEX>.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">03-01-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2147EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960403.0586 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=i pri=u> A7900 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-CRASH-PLANE-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">04-03</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-CRASH-PLANE-NYT
TWO PRIOR CRASHES OF 737S STILL UNSOLVED
(With CRASH-<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">BROWN</ENAMEX>-NYT)
(HLW)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX> plane that crashed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Croatia</ENAMEX> on
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> was a modified version of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 737, a widely used
aircraft with one of the best safety records in the air. But two
unexplained crashes in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">the last five years</TIMEX>, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> and
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colorado Springs</ENAMEX>, have raised questions about the 737's
performance.
<p>
   Like the plane that crashed on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX>, those aircraft crashed
while approaching airports for landing. But it is not known if
there are any similarities between the crashes in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX>
and the crash in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Croatia</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The investigators in the crash on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> may be lacking one
basic tool available to those probing the civilian crashes. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air
Force</ENAMEX> public affairs office at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> said that the plane,
like many of its aircraft, did not carry a cockpit voice recorder
or a flight data recorder, which are commonly known as black boxes.
However, a spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. European Command</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Stuttgart</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>, contradicted that, saying such equipment was aboard.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> crash, of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USAir</ENAMEX> flight from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> that
crashed on an airport approach in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1994</TIMEX>, is the most intensively
studied crash in the history of American civil aviation, but safety
experts still do not know what caused it. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colorado Springs</ENAMEX>
crash, in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX>, is also unexplained; transportation officials hope
the investigation of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> crash will help explain it.
<p>
   The 737 is the single most popular commercial jet, and it makes
up about a quarter of the American airline jet fleet. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> has
sold over 1,100 of the 737-200s, the model that crashed on
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX>, and over 2,800 of all types of 737s, with 500 more on
order.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX> bought 19, including the one that crashed on
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX>, for <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$5.4 million</NUMEX> each, and they were delivered in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1973</TIMEX>
and <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1974</TIMEX>. Most are used for training navigators. Until <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX>,
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX> had never had a crash involving the planes, or indeed
any incident that resulted in a death or permanent disability.
<p>
   The plane that crashed had recorded 12,000 landings and 17,000
hours of flight, which made it a relatively young aircraft, said
Maj. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Laura J. Feldman</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX>. The plane was
flying from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tuzla</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dubrovnik</ENAMEX>, a 45-minute trip.
<p>
   Among the characteristics that make the 737 desirable for the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX> is its ability to operate from short, rough airfields.
<p>
   The plane that crashed, called a T-43 by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX>, was set
up to carry about 60 passengers. It had fewer windows than the
airline model and some extra electronic equipment protruding from
its stubby, 100-foot-long body.
<p>
   The plane had been used in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bosnia</ENAMEX> in recent weeks to ferry
American and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NATO</ENAMEX> dignitaries to and from airports where many
runways have been scarred by civil war. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX> officials say
during a visit to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Balkans</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">earlier this year</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The plane had been used <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">earlier this week</TIMEX> to ferry <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Defense</ENAMEX>
Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Perry</ENAMEX> on trips within the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Balkans</ENAMEX>  &MD;  from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Zagreb</ENAMEX>,
the Croatian capital, to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tuzla</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sarajevo</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bosnia</ENAMEX>, and then to
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tirana</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Albania</ENAMEX>, and from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Albania</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cairo</ENAMEX> on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Tuesday</TIMEX>. Military
officials said that the plane then returned to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Zagreb</ENAMEX> to pick up
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Commerce</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ron Brown</ENAMEX> and his delegation.
<p>
   For security, the crew minimized time at low altitudes, to limit
the possibility of the plane being hit by gunfire or shells fired
by rebel forces, according to officials.
<p>
   The plane, clearly marked with a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> flag on its tail and the
bold lettering ``<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States of America</ENAMEX>'' on its side, was based
at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ramstein Air Base</ENAMEX>, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>, as was its crew. The civilian
version has a crew of three; the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX> said that the plane that
crashed had six crewmen on board.
<p>
   Investigators working on the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> crash say they believe
that the aircraft's trajectory on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> can be explained only
by a sudden, full swing of the rudder on its tail, but the parts
that survived the wreckage do not provide any physical evidence
that this actually occurred, and the flight data recorder was not
sophisticated enough to record the information.
<p>
federal agency in charge of investigating civilian aircraft
accidents, hopes to finish the investigation and reach a conclusion
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this year</TIMEX>.
<p>
   Apart from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colorado Springs</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX>, the agency has only
three unsolved crashes in its <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">29-year</TIMEX> history.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Safety Board</ENAMEX> is sending several investigators with the
military team to look into the crash.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">04-03-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2047EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960403.0686 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=r> A8015 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tth-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">BROWN</ENAMEX>-PLANE-SPI </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">04-03</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">BROWN</ENAMEX>-PLANE-SPI
PLANE'S CRASH AGAIN RAISES QUESTIONS ABOUT ITS CIVILIAN COUSIN, THE
737
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients.)
(With <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">BROWN</ENAMEX>-CRASH)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">T.M. SELL</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Seattle Post-Intelligencer</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   The jet that crashed <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Commerce</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ron
Brown</ENAMEX> and 32 others aboard was a military derivative of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>
737  &MD;  similar in many ways to the civilian model but different in
that it had no in-flight voice or data recorders.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> sold 19 of the T-43 models to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> government in
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1973-74</TIMEX> for use as trainers. A couple, like the one that crashed
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX>, were later refitted to carry passengers.
<p>
   The T-43 is basically a 737-200 model with a reinforced floor to
support training equipment and with fewer windows. Most of the
fleet is involved in training flight navigators for other <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>
military aircraft, stationed at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX> bases around the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United
States</ENAMEX>. The plane that crashed was stationed at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ramstein Air Force
Base</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> as part of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">76th Airlift Squadron</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The tragedy again raises questions about the 737, if only
because the well-traveled jetliner has been involved in a pair of
unsolved crashes in recent years. A <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">March 3, 1991</TIMEX>, crash of a
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX> 737 near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colorado Springs</ENAMEX> killed 25 people. The
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Sept. 8, 1994</TIMEX>, crash of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USAir</ENAMEX> 737 near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Alequippa</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX>, in which
132 people died, remains under investigation.
<p>
   In both accidents, the aircraft rolled sharply and crashed.
Federal investigations into the crashes have centered on
unexplained movements of the rudder. About a dozen such incidents,
not involving crashes, have been recorded on 737 flights.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Air Force</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> representatives said they have no
immediate explanations for <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX>'s crash in the coastal
mountains of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Croatia</ENAMEX>. The 22-year-old aircraft had modern safety
equipment and was certified for instrument flying in the type of
stormy weather reported in the area at the time of the crash.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Russ Young</ENAMEX> said the company will send experts
to support the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX>'s investigation of the crash.
<p>
   That investigation will be hampered by the T-43's lack of the
``black box'' recorders that are standard equipment on commercial
jets. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Force</ENAMEX> Maj. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Felicity Tavares</ENAMEX> said the T-43 was equipped
only with a ground-proximity warning system and standard commercial
navigational aids.
<p>
   The airplane had logged about 17,000 hours of flying time and
had 12,000 take-off and landing cycles. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> officials say that's
not much by normal commercial standards, and especially not for a
737, which is designed for frequent, short-haul service.
<p>
   Aerospace industry officials say the crash underscores the
challenge facing modern aviation, to reduce the number of crashes
even as the number of flights increases.
<p>
   The challenge is particularly acute for the 737. With more than
2,600 jets in service and more than 3,300 ordered, the 737 is the
world's best-selling jetliner. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> executives and many observers
argue that, considering its tremendous number of flights in all
conditions, the 737 is as safe as any aircraft.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tim Neale</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Transport Association</ENAMEX>, which represents
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> airlines, said that the incidence of accidents has fallen by
half over the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">past 15 years</TIMEX>. But the rising number of flights makes
it sometimes appear that the chance of a crash is increasing.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">From 1979 to 1994</TIMEX>, the number of fatal accidents was 1 per 1.8
million flights, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Neale</ENAMEX> said, vs. 1 per 814,000 flights <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">from 1963 to
1978</TIMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bob Robeson</ENAMEX>, vice president of civil aviation for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aerospace
Industries Association</ENAMEX>, a manufacturers' group, said the
improvements have flowed from advancements in technology as well as
training.
<p>
   ``Controlled flight into terrain'' was a leading cause of
crashes until the advent of the ground-proximity warning system,
which tells pilots when they're too close to the ground, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robeson</ENAMEX>
said.
<p>
   ``Human factors''  &MD;  such as improved training, improved
flight-deck design and improved maintenance  &MD;  also have played a
large role in improving safety, he said.
<p>
   Still, the severity of air crashes, no matter how rare, makes
the safety issue one of constant concern. Industry officials
acknowledge that if the public doesn't think it's safe to fly,
they'll be out of business.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">04-03-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2231EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960411.0354 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A5729 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=ttj-z> BC-PLANE-CRASH-HNS </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">04-11</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-PLANE-CRASH-HNS
GIRL, FATHER, INSTRUCTOR KILLED IN PLANE CRASH
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients.)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">LARRY D. HATFIELD</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">ERIN McCORMICK</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">San Francisco Examiner</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">SAN FRANCISCO</ENAMEX>  &MD;  A 7-year-old <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pescadero</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, girl's dream of
making history by flying coast-to-coast in both directions ended in
tragedy <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">morning</TIMEX> when her light plane crashed in a
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cheyenne</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wyo.</ENAMEX>, rain, hail and snowstorm, killing her, her father
and her flight instructor.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jessica Dubroff</ENAMEX>, her father, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lloyd Dubroff</ENAMEX>, 57, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Mateo</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, corporate consultant, and her flight instructor and
co-pilot, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joe Reid</ENAMEX>, 52, all perished when the four-seat <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cessna</ENAMEX>
Skyhawk went down in a residential neighborhood <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">seconds after it's
<TIMEX TYPE="TIME">7:24 PDT</TIMEX> takeoff in heavy rain, mixed with light hail and snow</TIMEX>.
<p>
   ``We don't have any details except we are not expecting any
patients,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ginger Humphrey</ENAMEX>, a spokeswoman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Medical
Center</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Witness <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tom Johnson</ENAMEX>, a pilot, said it appeared the pilot was
trying to return to the airport in the face of the rapidly
developing storm when ``it stalled over my building, winged over
and went straight into the ground like a dart.''
<p>
   ``I kept thinking, `Please, please get some altitude,''' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Johnson</ENAMEX>
said, saying the plane never got more than 400 feet off the ground.
``It just went right into the ground. I knew no one survived. It
would have been impossible.''
<p>
   It was not immediately known who was at the controls, said
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cheyenne</ENAMEX> police spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dick Royce</ENAMEX>. But the ground rules for the
record attempt were that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reid</ENAMEX> was to touch the controls only in an
emergency and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dubroff</ENAMEX> was to ride in the back seat.
<p>
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX> said the small plane crashed about a mile north of the
airport after taking off to the west.
<p>
   ``It went in nose first,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dawn Salyards</ENAMEX>, a resident of the
area. ``From the looks of it you could tell, pretty much right
away, that there would be no survivors.''
<p>
   It barely missed one house, landing at the end of the driveway,
witnesses said. Debris was scattered throughout the neighborhood in
this quiet prairie city of about 50,000. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> and police said
fuel spilled but there was no fire.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">Within 20 minutes of the crash</TIMEX>, a tarp had been placed over the
plane. The only sections visible were the tail and wings, which
were crumpled.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mike Benson</ENAMEX>, spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Transportation Safety
Board</ENAMEX>, which investigates 2,000 plane crashes a year, said a team
was enroute from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX> to probe the crash.
<p>
   ``We will be looking at all aspects of the accident, from the
human factors to the mechanical,'' he said.
<p>
   Certain to be a focus of the investigation was the stunt itself,
the type of flight  &MD;  and pilot  &MD;  many air safety experts say should
be discouraged.
<p>
   ``The Guinness Book of Records'' had ceased recognizing the
``youngest pilot'' category for fear of encouraging unsafe flights.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Barker</ENAMEX>, would not comment on the potential danger of
such record-breaking attempts. ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> was aware that there was a
record attempt being made by the 7-year-old,'' he said. ``This is
not the first time something like this has been attempted by
minors.
<p>
   ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>'s position is that the flight instructor is in
control. The 7-year-old was considered a passenger (and) was not
considered to be in control of the plane.''
<p>
   The minimum age for a pilot's license is 16.
<p>
   Before the flight, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jessica</ENAMEX>'s father said the girl ``dragged her
mother and me into this'' and was not pushed by parental ambition.
<p>
   ``If she can do this, she can do anything,'' he said. ``And it
will expand her horizons. She's going see the country slide by
under her wing at 150 knots ... and she's going to be able to say,
`I did that.'''
<p>
   A man who answered the <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reid</ENAMEX> home telephone in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Half Moon Bay</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, shortly after the crash, said, ``I'm sorry, we're not
making any comments right now.''
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dubroff</ENAMEX> home telephone was not answered.
<p>
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">04-11-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1458EDT</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960503.0801 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A4130 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">IND</ENAMEX>-AIRCRASH-REPORT-N </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">05-03</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0726 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">IND</ENAMEX>-AIRCRASH-REPORT-NYT
REPORT RELEASED ON <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">INDIANA</ENAMEX> CRASH THAT KILLED 68
(bl)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">ADAM BRYANT</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX> 
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Eighteen months after an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Eagle</ENAMEX> turboprop plane crashed
in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Roselawn</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ind.</ENAMEX>, killing all 68 people aboard,</TIMEX> the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal
Aviation Administration</ENAMEX> issued its answers <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this week</TIMEX> to one series
of questions raised by the accident. And <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Monday</TIMEX>, the agency begins
addressing new questions raised by the very same crash.
<p>
   Since the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Roselawn</ENAMEX> crash, the agency has worked to gain a better
understanding of the effects of flying in icy weather, in
particular a rare condition in which tiny droplets of water are
suspended in the atmosphere below freezing temperature.
<p>
   When those liquid droplets strike a surface like an airplane
wing, they freeze on contact. Investigators believe a ridge of ice
formed on the wing of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Eagle</ENAMEX> turboprop  &MD;  an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ATR</ENAMEX>-72  &MD; 
causing it to tilt uncontrollably and crash.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> issued a series of so-called airworthiness
directives affecting 29 types of turboprop aircraft  &MD;  the kind
typically used by regional commuter airlines  &MD;  that have a long
rubber bladder along the leading edge of their wings to crack and
shed ice.
<p>
   The regulations instruct pilots to look for signs of ice
accumulating on windows, wings or propeller hubs. If they see it,
they are supposed to change altitude or direction quickly.
<p>
   To reach that relatively simple ruling, however, required an
enormous amount of testing of these aircraft by the aviation agency
and their manufacturers.
<p>
   Those tests included measuring the tilting forces created while
taxiing at high-speeds with wooden shapes attached to the wings. In
addition, some aircraft were flown behind a tanker plane, which
sprayed them with water to see how they would perform in such
conditions.
<p>
   The aviation agency has determined that the French-made <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ATR</ENAMEX>
aircraft were the only turboprop commuter planes now flying in the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> that required a design modification.
<p>
   The manufacturer, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Avions de Transport Regional</ENAMEX>, with the
agency's approval, agreed to enlarge the rubber bladder along the
leading edge so that it covered more of the top of the wing. An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ATR</ENAMEX>
spokeswoman said the company had modified the wings of all its
aircraft worldwide that flew in conditions where such icy weather
might occur.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Anthony J. Broderick</ENAMEX>, the agency's associate administrator for
regulation and certification, said that because the tests were so
rigorous, he was confident that a crash like the one in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Roselawn</ENAMEX>
would not occur again.
<p>
   ``We have closed the door on the safety issues,'' he said. He
added that since <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Roselawn</ENAMEX>, no airlines or pilots had filed reports
on planes upset in icy weather.
<p>
   Even so, questions about icy weather remain, and many of them
will be discussed starting <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Monday</TIMEX> during a <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">three-day</TIMEX> conference on
in-flight icing at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Springfield</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Va.</ENAMEX> About 400 aviation experts from
the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> and many foreign countries are expected to
attend.
<p>
   Those and other discussions may lead, in months or even years,
to new standards that manufacturers must meet before the aviation
agency certifies their aircraft.
<p>
   The current standards have been in place since the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1940s</TIMEX>, and
were not changed after a review in the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1960s</TIMEX>. In broad terms, those
standards take into account most weather conditions that occur most
of the time.
<p>
   But as more turboprops fly more frequently, the chances of
encountering the rare but hazardous condition known as
``super-cooled drizzle drops'' rises.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Broderick</ENAMEX> said his agency's goals included developing better
ways to forecast these conditions and possibly develop equipment to
alert pilots that they are flying in such conditions. Generally,
these conditions occur in relatively narrow bands in the sky, and
experts say that changing altitude by 2,000 or 3,000 feet is often
enough to escape the situation.
<p>
   The aviation agency is currently spending about <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$400,000</NUMEX> a year
on research into the problem. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Broderick</ENAMEX> said the agency also
planned to start testing some smaller aircraft that are not used by
commercial airlines but that do use the rubber de-icing system.
<p>
accidents, is expected to issue its conclusions about what caused
the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Roselawn</ENAMEX> crash <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">within two months</TIMEX>.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">05-03-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2123EDT</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960508.2452 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A2227 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MARINE</ENAMEX>-CRASH-600&AMP;ADD- </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">05-11</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 1021 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MARINE</ENAMEX>-CRASH-600&AMP;ADD-2NDLD-NYT
(<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mo.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX> ATTN)
HELICOPTER CRASH KILLS 14 MARINES
(inserts new material after 3rd graf to give some of victims'
names)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">RONALD SMOTHERS</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CAMP LEJEUNE</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.C.</ENAMEX>  &MD;  Fourteen marines were killed and two were
injured <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">before dawn</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Friday</TIMEX> when two helicopters collided and
plunged into a densely forested marsh in an isolated part of this
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marine Corps</ENAMEX> base in eastern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North Carolina</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The cause of the crash, which happened at <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2 a.m.</TIMEX> during a huge
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>-British amphibious-assault exercise, is still under
investigation, officials said.
<p>
   Of the injured, one was listed in critical condition at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pitt
County Memorial Hospital</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Greenville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.C.</ENAMEX>, and the other was
listed in serious condition at the base hospital. No British troops
were involved in the crash.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">The Associated Press</ENAMEX> reported that officials at the base
identified three of the dead as First Lt. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Arthur J. Schneider</ENAMEX> of
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Livingston</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>,; Maj. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael D. Kuszewski</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fort Devens</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>
and Capt. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Scott T. Rice</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Springfield</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mo.</ENAMEX>
<p>
   By <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">midafternoon</TIMEX> 11 bodies of the crash victims had been
recovered from the scene. But it took until about <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">4:30 p.m.</TIMEX> for the
final three bodies to be recovered from the muddy and wooded area
where rescuers toiled for more than <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">16 hours</TIMEX>. It was an indication,
a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">marine</ENAMEX> spokesman said, of the conditions in the forest.
<p>
   The search was hampered as tractors sank up to their tread tops
in the muck and rescuers resorted to cutting pathways with
chainsaws and fashioning walkways over the shifting ground with
slabs of plywood.
<p>
   ``It is very thick pine forest and swamp,'' said Maj. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve
Little</ENAMEX>, a spokesman. ``It has been difficult, especially difficult
<TIMEX TYPE="TIME" MIN="dawn">before dawn</TIMEX> as we began the recovery. It has been made easier with
more light.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Little</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">marines</ENAMEX> were part of a joint exercise including
38,200 <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> troops and 15,600 British troops. The helicopters
involved were an AH-1W Super Cobra attack helicopter with a
two-person crew and a CH-46E Sea Knight, an assault and transport
helicopter that can carry as many as 22 people in addition to its
crew of four.
<p>
   The helicopters had taken off <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">earlier that night</TIMEX> from ships
massed off the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">North Carolina</ENAMEX> coast and headed inland to where the
accident occurred near the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Courthouse Bay</ENAMEX> boat basin at the
150,000-acre military base.
<p>
   Flight operations in the British-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> exercises were suspended,
although surface operations would continue, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Little</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Friday</TIMEX>'s accident was deadliest for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marine Corps</ENAMEX> since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1989</TIMEX>,
when 14 people were killed in the crash of another Sea Knight off
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Okinawa</ENAMEX>. More than twice as many marines have died in aviation
accidents in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">the last eight months</TIMEX> as were killed in such accidents
in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">the previous two years</TIMEX>. The total killed so far <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this year</TIMEX> in
aviation accidents, counting <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Friday</TIMEX>'s deaths, is 19. In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1995</TIMEX> there
were six aviation deaths and in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1994</TIMEX> there were only three such
deaths.
<p>
   It was a Harrier jet crash here in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1993</TIMEX> that prompted the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marine
Corps</ENAMEX> to order a rare 48-hour suspension of all fixed-wing and
helicopter flights to conduct emergency safety checks. In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">that
year</TIMEX>, 12 people were killed in aircraft accidents. As recently as
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">March</TIMEX> the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Marine Corps</ENAMEX> called another two-day halt to all aircraft
flights for emergency checks.
<p>
   Col. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joe C. Yannessa</ENAMEX>, commander of the rescue operation, said
the collision had occurred in midair over the densely pine-forested
marshland and rained debris over a 150 yard area. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yannessa</ENAMEX> said
rescue crews on foot and carrying nothing more than their packs and
hand-held fire extinguishers got to the section of swamp 600 yards
from the nearest road <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">within 30 minutes of the crash</TIMEX>. There were
several smoldering, but not intense, fires scattered throughout the
area, he said.
<p>
   ``The aircraft frankly is in such a state of destruction that
there are no identifying marks that we could see on the aircraft,''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Yannessa</ENAMEX> said. ``They were sunk 3 to 4 to 5 feet into the muck.''
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">05-11-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">0025EDT</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960511.0219 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A2578 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tad-z> BC-CRASH-MAIN-COX </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">05-11</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0780 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-CRASH-MAIN-COX
109 FEARED DEAD IN <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">EVERGLADES</ENAMEX> CRASH
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">GEORGE BENNETT</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cox News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">MIAMI</ENAMEX>  &MD;  A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ValuJet</ENAMEX> DC-9 jetliner headed for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlanta</ENAMEX> with 109
people on board crashed in the marshy <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Everglades</ENAMEX> about 20 miles
northwest of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami International Airport</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Saturday</TIMEX>.
<p>
   Flight 592 plunged into a swampy expanse of sawgrass more about
10 miles from the nearest road in an area accessible only by
100 miles west of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> when its pilot reported smoke in the
cockpit and turned to go back to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> shortly after <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2 p.m.</TIMEX>
<p>
   An eyewitness said the plane dived nose down at a 75-degree
angle.
<p>
   ``Nothing could have survived that,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Daniel Muelhaupt</ENAMEX>, who
told <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CNN</ENAMEX> he was piloting a private plane with a student and was
about two miles from the DC-9.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Muelhaupt</ENAMEX> said he first thought the plane was a smaller craft
practicing maneuvers. He saw no smoke or fire coming from the
plane, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Muelhaupt</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   His flying student, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rick DeLisle</ENAMEX>, told <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">CNN</ENAMEX> the impact of the
plane created a mushroom cloud about 100 feet high.
<p>
   ``It just looked like a large trash bag was blown open,''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">DeLisle</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   The plane crashed into at least four feet of water and debris
sank into several feet of muck below, fire-rescue officials said.
<p>
   All that was visible from the air was flotsam spread over a
50-yard area.
<p>
   The crash site is about 20 miles northwest of the airport in an
area inhabited primarily by snakes, alligators and mosquitos.
Rescue workers put out a call for anti-venin as a precaution
against possible snake bites.
<p>
   ``Accessibility is extremely difficult,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Metro-Dade</ENAMEX> Lt.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Luis Fernandez</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   ``You cannot see the total fuselage,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">R.D. Paulison</ENAMEX>,
director of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Metro-Dade Fire Rescue</ENAMEX>. ``There were no tail pieces to
see. There were no wing pieces to see. There was nothing at all.''
<p>
   A sheen of highly flammable aviation fuel on the water hampered
initial rescue efforts and attempts to recover the plane's flight
recorder, or ``black box.''
<p>
recorder aboard Flight 592 was an older model that would not
provide as many clues to the crash as newer, more sophisticated
models.
<p>
   A plane crash in a swamp is one of the worst-case scenarios in
the rescue business, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Wright</ENAMEX>, a special operations chief
for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Palm Beach County Fire Rescue</ENAMEX>, which practiced such a rescue
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last month</TIMEX>.
<p>
   Between the waist-deep watery mud, sawgrass so sharp it can
slice rescue worker's gear and the alligators and snakes, access is
a nightmare, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wright</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   Along the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tamiami Trail</ENAMEX> about 10 miles south of the crash site,
dozens of private airboat owners lined the road volunteering their
services to rescue workers. By <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">nightfall</TIMEX>, though, authorities had
sent them home, and police were turning away visitors.
<p>
   Rescue and recovery workers were setting up camp <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Saturday</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">night</TIMEX>
near the site along the levee of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">L-67 Canal</ENAMEX>, hanging mosquito
netting and lights from their boats as they settled in for the
<TIMEX TYPE="TIME">night</TIMEX>.
<p>
   At <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami International Airport</ENAMEX>, about 50 or 60 family members of
Flight 592 passengers arrived in <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">the first 2{ hours after the crash</TIMEX>
and were shepherded to a private area where counselors and clergy
were on hand.
<p>
   It was the first crash of a commercial flight arriving or
departing at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami International</ENAMEX> since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">December 1972</TIMEX>, when an
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern Airlines</ENAMEX> L-1011 crashed in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Everglades</ENAMEX> approaching the
airport and 101 of 176 aboard were killed.
<p>
   It was the first fatal accident involving <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ValuJet</ENAMEX> since the
bargain airline began operations in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">October 1993</TIMEX>.
<p>
   But <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ValuJet</ENAMEX> has had several safety problems over <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">the last year</TIMEX>.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">June</TIMEX>, an engine fire spread through the fuselage of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ValuJet</ENAMEX>
plane on the runway at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hartsfield International Airport</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlanta</ENAMEX>,
burning a flight attendant and destroying the plane.
<p>
   Since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">January</TIMEX>, three <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ValuJet</ENAMEX> planes have run off runways in bad
weather, and two planes have been knocked out of service after hard
landings. There were no injuries in any of those incidents.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlanta</ENAMEX>-based carrier began with two used planes in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1993</TIMEX> and
has expanded to about 50. But it announced <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last month</TIMEX> it would take
a break from its rapid growth ``to concentrate on its product
integrity prior to the commencement of the Olympic Games,'' the
airline said.
<p>
   ``This decision has been made, in part, in response to increased
(<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>) scrutiny and requirements relating to the company that
resulted from recent incidents involving the company's aircraft,''
the airline said at the time.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">05-11-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2156EDT</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960515.0838 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A7212 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tad-z> BC-CRASH-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CHICAG</ENAMEX>-COX </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">05-15</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0753 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-CRASH-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CHICAG</ENAMEX>-COX
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1986</TIMEX> COMMERCIAL FLIGHT EXPERIENCED SIMILAR FIRE, EXPLOSION TO
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VALUJET</ENAMEX> PLANE
EDs: With CRASH-MAIN.
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">SIOBHAN MORRISSEY</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cox News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WEST PALM BEACH</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fla.</ENAMEX>  &MD;  Half an hour after a mechanic jostled an
oxygen-generating canister aboard a grounded <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">McDonnell Douglas</ENAMEX>
DC-10, the airplane began smoldering and then erupted into flames.
<p>
   Although no one was injured, flames destroyed the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Trans
Air</ENAMEX> jetliner shortly after it arrived from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Honolulu</ENAMEX> on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Aug. 10,
investigators are exploring whether a similar fire could have
caused <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ValuJet</ENAMEX> 592 to crash into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Everglades</ENAMEX>, killing all 110
(CQ) people on board.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ValuJet</ENAMEX>'s cargo manifest listed five crates containing 50 to 60
of the stainless steel canisters that produce oxygen for emergency
masks. The devices were stowed near three inflated aircraft spare
tires.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robert Francis</ENAMEX>, the board's vice chairman, said the oxygen
generators may have exploded in the forward cargo hold.
<p>
   Such an explosion could account for why the air speed and
altimeter registered information that conflicted with radar reports
of how fast and how high the plane was traveling, chief
investigator <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gregory Feith</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   Similarly, the aircraft tires pose a potential problem for
in-air explosion. Former safety board chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jim Burnett</ENAMEX>
described the aircraft tires as ``very dangerous to be around
because they are under very high pressure  &MD;  if you are around one
when it blows it can kill you.''
<p>
   Sometimes tires that are part of the landing gear explode while
in flight but they do not damage the aircraft because a special
shield in the wheel well protects the aircraft, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Burnett</ENAMEX> said.
However, the cargo hold lacks such shielding, he said.
<p>
   ``I've heard of tires exploding in the wheel well, but never ran
across the issue of them being transported in the cargo,'' he said.
``I rather suspect that's because they don't do it.''
<p>
   Other safety board officials registered concern about proper use
of oxygen generating systems as early as <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1976</TIMEX>.
<p>
   ``The potential for serious injuries and fatalities is great,''
an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> report said then, noting recurring problems with the
systems that chemically generate oxygen on DC-10s and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lockheed</ENAMEX>
1011s.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Department of Transportation</ENAMEX> classifies the oxygen
generators as hazardous materials when carried as company material
in cargo compartments. They should be packaged and stowed securely.
<p>
   Just as in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ValuJet</ENAMEX> case, oxygen generators were stowed in
the forward cargo compartment of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Trans Air</ENAMEX> plane what
was demolished in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> fire <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">10 years ago</TIMEX>. An <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Trans
Air</ENAMEX> mechanic apparently set off the fire that destroyed the DC-10
while attempting to fix an oxygen compartment door that would not
close.
<p>
   ``He found a loose oxygen canister and handled it improperly by
its oxygen hose,'' according to a safety board account of the fire.
That released the firing pin, which in turn fired the percussion
cap and triggered a chemical reaction that generated oxygen.
<p>
   Improper handling of the oxygen generating canisters -- such as
