<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960103.0355 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A1061 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tdt-z> BC-CHILD-SEATS-BOS </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-03</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-CHILD-SEATS-BOS
AIR ACCIDENTS SPUR MOVE TO ALTER RULES ON SEATING OF BABIES
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW BRELIS</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">The Boston Globe</ENAMEX>
    The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USAir</ENAMEX> flight attendant in the rear of the plane making a
short flight to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Charlotte</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.C.</ENAMEX>, kept peeking around the corner of
a seat in Row 21, making 9-month-old <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Danasia Brown</ENAMEX> laugh.
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   Like most of the two million infants under 2 who fly with their
parents every year, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Danasia</ENAMEX> was traveling for free, seated on her
mother's lap.
<p>
   As the DC-9 approached the airport on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">July 2, 1994</TIMEX>, wind shear
slammed the plane to the ground.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tywonda Brown</ENAMEX>'s daughter was flung out of her arms. ``I tried to
hold on to her,'' she told federal safety investigators. ``I tried
to hold her and I couldn't.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Danasia</ENAMEX> died of blunt force trauma after being hurled through
the plane at more than 120 miles per hour, battered by several
seats and parts of the cabin. She was one of 37 people to die in
the crash.
<p>
to get the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Aviation Administration</ENAMEX> to require that children
under 2 wear child-safety restraint systems, such as those in cars.
<p>
   In a letter <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last May</TIMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> administrator <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">David Hinson</ENAMEX>, the
board's chairman, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Hall</ENAMEX>, referred to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Danasia</ENAMEX>, saying, ``The
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Safety Board</ENAMEX> believes that if the child had been properly
restrained in a child restraint system, she might not have
sustained fatal injuries.''
<p>
   ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Safety Board</ENAMEX> is disappointed with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>'s inadequate
actions regarding the required use of child restraint systems,''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hall</ENAMEX> wrote.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Association of Flight Attendants</ENAMEX>, a union representing more
than 36,000 flight attendants at 24 airlines, is even more
emphatic.
<p>
   ``It is inconceivable, given the strict rules of everything on
the aircraft  &MD;  from coffee pots to carry-on baggage  &MD;  that must be
tied down or securely stowed for takeoff and landing, or in flight
when the captain thinks it is necessary, that the same
consideration is not given to human beings, even though they are
under the age of 2,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Patricia Friend</ENAMEX>, president of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">AFA</ENAMEX>, which
started a public education campaign <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">earlier this year</TIMEX> calling for
mandatory use of child restraint seats.
<p>
   So far, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>, which regulates commercial aviation and ensures
the safety of the flying public, has refused to demand safety seats
for infants.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">June</TIMEX> the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> released a report to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Congress</ENAMEX> that theorized
many families faced with purchasing a seat for an infant, estimated
to add <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$200</NUMEX> to the cost of the trip, would take to the highways
rather than fly. <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Over 10 years</TIMEX>, some 82 children whose parents
decided to drive rather than fly, would die in traffic accidents,
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> predicted.
<p>
   At the same time, the number of infants killed in commercial air
crashes is extremely low. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> attributes the deaths of five
children in the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last eight years</TIMEX> to lack of safety restraints.
<p>
   ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> wants to educate parents rather than mandate a rule,''
said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> spokeswoman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alison Duquette</ENAMEX>. ``We would force many parents
with young children onto the road.''
<p>
   However, advocates for laws requiring child seats &UR;  &LR; note that the
airlines fight to keep customers and the industry devised frequent
flier rewards. Proponents of safety seats are confident the
industry would come up with a pricing scheme to keep the <NUMEX TYPE="PERCENT">one
percent</NUMEX> of all passengers who fly with infants.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Air Transport Association</ENAMEX>, representing 21 commercial
carriers, agreed.
<p>
   ``It is always difficult as an association to make comments
about pricing because of antitrust laws,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ATA</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tim
Neale</ENAMEX>. ``But certainly, (they) make a good point.''
<p>
   While <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ATA</ENAMEX> advocated mandates in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1990</TIMEX>, it now wants the
government to determine which child seats perform well and which
ones do not before implementing regulations.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>'s civil aeromedical institute in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Oklahoma City</ENAMEX> studied
child restraint systems and found that infants under 20 pounds
should be in aft facing safety seats and children two or older, but
under 40 pounds, should be in front-facing safety seats. Some
safety seats, such as booster seats, belly belts, and normal seat
belts for children under 40 pounds, did not provide adequate
protection.
<p>
   ``If you don't have your child restrained, it really doesn't
much matter in a high-impact accident,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> investigator
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nora Marshall</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Henry Hughes</ENAMEX>, another <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> survival specialist investigator said
that even at slow speeds, a parent's arms are not
enough &UR;  &LR; to &UR;  &LR; restrain a child.
<p>
   ``I know it must be very frustrating for parents, particularly
in an emergency, but when it comes right down to it, if the child
is not restrained, there is very little protection,'' said
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Marshall</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sylvia Tsao</ENAMEX> found that out with devastating results.
<p>
   She and her 22-month-old son, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Evan</ENAMEX>, were on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Airlines</ENAMEX>
Flight 232 from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Denver</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Chicago</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1989</TIMEX> when the tail engine blew
apart, resulting in a loss of all hydraulic power needed to control
the airplane.
<p>
   The 285 passengers and crew of 10 had more than 30 minutes to
prepare for an emergency landing at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sioux City</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Iowa</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Flight attendants, including <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jan Brown-Lohr</ENAMEX>, instructed
passengers on the brace position and told the parents of the four
lap infants to follow a prescribed procedure of wrapping their
children in blankets and pillows, and placing them on the floor of
the DC-10.
<p>
   ``I remember being in the brace position with my son's head
tucked between my knees, my left hand holding his ankle, my face
pushing down on his head, my legs outside his legs,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tsao</ENAMEX> told
investigators.
<p>
   ``Suddenly, the world seemed to end. I saw for an instant my
son's body floating and flying at a very high rate of speed down
the right aisle towards the back of the plane, his head first, his
face away from me. He must have been traveling at an incredible
speed.''
<p>
   When the plane stopped cartwheeling, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tsao</ENAMEX> shouted for her son,
but could not go back to where she thought he was. Another
passenger convinced her to leave the plane, which was quickly
filling with a choking smoke. It was the smoke, an autopsy
revealed, that killed <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Evan</ENAMEX>, not injuries from the crash.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown-Lohr</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Manchester</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.H.</ENAMEX>, native stayed in the plane until
the smoke forced her out.
<p>
   ``When I left, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sylvia</ENAMEX> was the first person I saw in the
cornfield,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown-Lohr</ENAMEX> recalled in an interview. ``She was trying
to go back to the plane. I stood in front of her and said, `You
can't go back.' She said she had to get her son and then said, `You
told me to put my baby on the floor and I did and now he's gone.'
<p>
   ``At that point, I didn't have any feeling at all. The hair on
the back of my neck stood up and I knew that I would have to live
with that for the rest of my life.
<p>
   ``I know what my responsiblity is: to keep every passenger in
the cabin safe. I cannot do that if a child is sitting on a lap.
The agency with responsibility for airline safety is the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> and
they are not doing their job.''
<p>
   Since the crash, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown-Lohr</ENAMEX> has worked to have child seats
mandated, either by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> or through legislation. <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Next month</TIMEX>, she
said she will come to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boston</ENAMEX> to give <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United</ENAMEX> crew members letters to
send to their representatives urging action.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown-Lohr</ENAMEX> has not spoken to <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tsao</ENAMEX> since their encounter in the
cornfield. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tsao</ENAMEX>, who now lives in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Mexico</ENAMEX>, declined to comment
about the accident. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown</ENAMEX> says she hopes to speak with <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tsao</ENAMEX> one
day.
<p>
   ``I am waiting until we succeed with this campaign. I couldn't
do anything for him that day, but this is what I can do and it
could give his life some meaning.''
<p>
   Some parents have voluntarily started buying seats for their
infants under two  &MD;  and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brown-Lohr</ENAMEX> praises them every time she sees
one on a flight.
<p>
   But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Tywonda Brown</ENAMEX> was told it was not necessary.
<p>
   ``They told me I could hold her on my lap. I would have paid for
her to sit in a seat,'' she said. ``I would have given my life for
her. She wasn't here that long. She just turned nine months old.''
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="TIME">01-03-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1442EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960108.0493 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A5852 </STORYID>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-08</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0745 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">England</ENAMEX>, and an Irish balloonist, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rory McCarthy</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Branson</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lindstrand</ENAMEX>, who have set several ballooning records,
were the first pilots of hot-air balloons to cross both the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic Ocean</ENAMEX>, in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1987</TIMEX>, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pacific</ENAMEX>, in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lindstrand</ENAMEX> said that because of unfavorable weather patterns
over <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">England</ENAMEX> he and his colleagues had decided to launch their
Virgin Global Challenger from a military airfield at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Marrakech</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Morocco</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   To move the big crew capsule, balloon and accessories, the
British group chartered a Beluga transport plane  &MD;  a modified
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Airbus</ENAMEX> 300 similar to the Pregnant Guppy aircraft used by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NASA</ENAMEX> to
transport large rocket components. The flight to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Morocco</ENAMEX> is
scheduled for <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Friday</TIMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Lindstrand</ENAMEX> said the balloon launching
would probably take place <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">a day or so later</TIMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Branson</ENAMEX>, chairman of the multifaceted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Virgin Group</ENAMEX>, which
includes <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Virgin Atlantic Airways</ENAMEX>, believes that his competitor,
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Fossett</ENAMEX>, faces grave risks.
<p>
   ``Because his capsule is not pressurized,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Branson</ENAMEX> said in an
interview, ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve</ENAMEX> will have to stay at around 20,000 feet, which
is usually well below the core of the jet stream. That could slow
him down a lot. We will be at 30,000 to 35,000 feet, where our
chances of riding the high-speed jet stream are much better.
<p>
   ``<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Steve</ENAMEX> is incredibly brave, and if anyone should beat us, I'd
rather it was he.''
<p>
   The Dutch team, led by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Henk Brink</ENAMEX>, recently tested the inflation
of its Unicef Flyer balloon at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cape Kennedy</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NASA</ENAMEX>'s huge Vehicle
Assembly Building, where space shuttles are prepared for flight.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brink</ENAMEX>, who intends to launch his balloon from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nijmegen</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">the
Netherlands</ENAMEX>, is a helicopter instructor and veteran balloonist.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1986</TIMEX>, he, his wife, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Evelien</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William Hageman</ENAMEX>, a Dutch
fighter pilot, became the first European balloonists to cross the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic</ENAMEX>; so precise was their navigation that they landed within a
few miles of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brink</ENAMEX>'s home in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">the Netherlands</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Although balloons must travel in the same direction as the wind
that carries them along, a pilot can navigate to some extent by
changing altitude to seek wind headed in the desired direction.
Even a small change in altitude can result in a large change in
direction.
<p>
   The Unicef Flyer flight suffered a setback <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Dec. 26</TIMEX> when its
third crew member, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wouter Bakker</ENAMEX>, resigned from the flight crew
``for personal reasons.''
<p>
   Days before the expected launching <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this week</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brink</ENAMEX> said in an
interview that he had advertised for a replacement, stipulating
that the third crew member should be an airline captain.
<p>
   ``We're down to three candidates,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Brink</ENAMEX> said <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Friday</TIMEX>, ``and all
of them are completely familiar with our navigation and
communication equipment. For the launch and landing, I will do the
piloting.''
<p>
   All three teams are flying Rozier balloons  &MD;  a type that has
achieved many long-distance records in recent years.
<p>
   A modern Rozier is kept aloft by helium gas, but to add extra
lift, the balloon is compartmentalized and the lower part can be
filled with hot air from a gas burner. This enables the balloon to
maintain altitude at night, when cold air and the lack of sunlight
cools the helium and lessens its lifting power.
<p>
as too dangerous.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-08-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1751EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960118.0717 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=f pri=r> A6561 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tth-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BOEING</ENAMEX>-ENGINE-SPI </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-18</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BOEING</ENAMEX>-ENGINE-SPI
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients.)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">KAREN WEST</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Seattle Post-Intelligencer</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">SEATTLE</ENAMEX>  &MD;  A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Business Week</ENAMEX> report questions the safety of
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>'s new 777 jetliner and says the company has been in a
``contentious debate'' with federal aviation officials over
possible design flaws.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">night</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> vigorously defended the company's newest
airplane and sharply criticized the magazine for publishing ``an
article with conclusions based on innuendo, hearsay and anonymous
sources.'' The company also said the magazine refused an invitation
for a briefing.
<p>
   In its latest edition out <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Business Week</ENAMEX> says senior
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Aviation Administration</ENAMEX> officials downplayed the safety
concerns of their own engineers in certification tests on the 777.
The story also says that <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">for more than two years</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> officials have
been engaged in a debate with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> over possible design flaws in
the aircraft's engines.
<p>
   Quoting mostly unidentified sources, the article says <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>
engineers feared that if a fan blade on one of the 777's engines
broke during flight, the engine would become unbalanced and produce
vibrations that could cause the aircraft to lose stability.
<p>
   ``It's an issue of safety,'' one unidentified <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> engine
specialist is quoted as saying. ``It could lead to catastrophe.''
<p>
   The magazine also quotes anonymous <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> sources who question
whether the airplane has been adequately tested.
<p>
   In reply, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> said: ``No one is more interested in building a
safe airplane than <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> and we stand behind the safety and
reliability of our products. No airplane in history has been tested
as thoroughly as the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 777.''
<p>
   The magazine says numerous sources told it during a four-month
investigation that pressure to meet <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>'s planned certification
date led the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> to overrule safety concerns.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Business Week</ENAMEX> reports that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> executives refused to comment
for the article, but <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> spokeswoman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Donna Mikov</ENAMEX> said the
magazine never acknowledged an offer for background briefings on
the certification process.
<p>
   She said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Business Week</ENAMEX> approached <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> with ``preconceived
data that had not been researched thoroughly.''
<p>
   ``It is clear to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Business Week</ENAMEX> only wanted answers
to specific speculative questions without prior knowledge and
background on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 777 project or the certification
process,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mikov</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   In the article, senior <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> officials in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>, defend
the aircraft and the agency's safety review process.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Sandra Allen</ENAMEX>, assistant <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> administrator for public affairs in
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>, said <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> that the agency had not yet read
the piece but that ``the record is clear that the testing and
analysis of the B-777 were unprecedented in their scope and
breadth.
<p>
   ``The certification process for this aircraft exceeded 125,000
staff hours by technical experts at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>. The agency maintains
complete confidence in the certification process.''
<p>
   The three makers of engines for the 777  &MD;  <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pratt &AMP; Whitney</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Electric</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls Royce</ENAMEX>  &MD;  also denied any problems, the
magazine says.
<p>
   But the magazine says there are serious concerns about the size
and weight of the fan blades in the 777 engines.
<p>
   Fan blade breaks have been reported in 24 other jet airliners
since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1990</TIMEX>, the article said. Although no crashes have resulted
from such breaks, the magazine says <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> safety experts fear that
with the greater size and weight of the 777's blades, a break might
shake the cockpit so badly that pilots could not read the flight
instruments, increasing the risk of a crash. Despite the worries,
the FAA sources say <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> appears to have done only limited
testing to see how the 777 would react if a blade broke.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> officials maintain they cooperated fully with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX>
``in conducting the most rigorous laboratory, ground and flight
testing program in the history of commercial aviation.''
<p>
   The company added: ``We stand behind that process and fully
support the regulatory agencies in meeting the stringent
requirements for testing and certifying all versions of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>
777.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>'s 777, a <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$4 billion</NUMEX> aircraft, is the world's largest
two-engine passenger jet. Its engines are the largest ever made for
a commercial airplane and have unusually heavy fan blades  &MD;  48
pounds in the largest configuration. The outer portions of 777
engines are so big that the body of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 737 could fit inside
one.
<p>
   Because the 777 is equipped with two engines instead of four,
airline pilot and passenger groups initially voiced concerns about
flying the computer-designed aircraft on long-range, over-water
routes.
<p>
   But <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last May</TIMEX> when the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> gave the 777 unprecedented approval to
fly extended-range twin-engine operations, known as ETOPs, those
same groups praised it as one of the most technologically advanced
in aviation history.
<p>
   As a result of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>'s flight-test program  &MD;  which included
1,000 takeoffs and landings to simulate a year's worth of
commercial service for one plane  &MD;  <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> officials said the 777 would
be ``the finest, most reliable and safest airplane ever
delivered.''
<p>
   During its testing program, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> was required to prove that,
in the event of a single-engine failure, the 777 could safely
continue flying for up to three hours.
<p>
   The 777, which began commercial service <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last June</TIMEX> with a flight
from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">D.C.</ENAMEX>, has captured more than <NUMEX TYPE="PERCENT">80 percent</NUMEX>
of the worldwide market for its class of aircraft since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1990</TIMEX>,
according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-18-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2313EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960131.0611 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A9510 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">HILL</ENAMEX>-OBIT-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-31</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">HILL</ENAMEX>-OBIT-NYT
(<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Del.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mo.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Mass.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX> ATTN)
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">JULIAN HILL</ENAMEX>, 91, WHO DISCOVERED NYLON
(lb)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">DAVID STOUT</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Julian Hill</ENAMEX>, a research chemist whose accidental discovery of a
tough, taffylike compound revolutionized everyday life after it
proved its worth in warfare and courtship, died on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Sunday</TIMEX> in
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hockessin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Del.</ENAMEX> He was 91.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> died at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cokesbury Village</ENAMEX> retirement community, where
he had lived in recent years with his wife <TIMEX TYPE="DATE" MIN="62 years">of 62 years</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Polly</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   During the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">late 1920s</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> was a member of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du Pont Co.</ENAMEX> team
studying the behavior of certain molecules that chain together to
form larger ones, called polymers. The chemists were engaged in
pure research, though finding a substitute for silk was in the back
of their minds.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1930</TIMEX>, while trying to create ever larger structures by
adjusting the amount of water in a batch of carbon- and
alcohol-based molecules, the team came up with a concoction that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du
Pont</ENAMEX>'s research head, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wallace Carothers</ENAMEX>, thought useless.
<p>
   But <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> was intrigued after sticking a heated glass rod into a
beaker containing the material and finding that it stretched and
pulled, like taffy, and that it became silky when stretched at room
temperature. Soon, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> and his colleagues were playing with the
material in the corridor and finding that it could be shaped into
strands that were remarkably long and strong.
<p>
   The substance, of course, was nylon, although it would not be so
named until it was introduced at the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1939</TIMEX> World's Fair in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>
 &MD;  hence, the ``ny'' in nylon.
<p>
   ``I tell my wife I was something better than a good scientist,''
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> recalled in an interview years later. ``I was lucky.'' Since
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du Pont</ENAMEX> held the patents to nylon, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> made no great fortune off
the discovery, but his wife said <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> that the company had
treated him well over the years.
<p>
   (A sad footnote is the fate of <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carothers</ENAMEX>. Beset by personal
problems that fueled depression, thinking himself a failure despite
a brilliant career, he committed suicide in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1937</TIMEX> at the age of 41.)
<p>
   If the development of nylon was in part serendipity, it was not
a total surprise. <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Almost a decade earlier</TIMEX>, at an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Chemical
Society</ENAMEX> conference in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Buffalo</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.Y.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Carothers</ENAMEX> reported on
progress in developing ``artificial silks'' like rayon, which was
then coming into use.
<p>
   But rayon is derived from cellulose and in that sense is not
strictly synthetic, as is nylon. Nylon was used initially for
toothbrush bristles, fishing line and surgical sutures. Nylon
stockings were first sold in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1939</TIMEX>. They cost twice what silk
stockings did, and women were happy to pay. Nylon stockings were
sheer and strong.
<p>
   The material was deemed so important that its use was restricted
to the military after the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> entered World War II. Nylon
was used to make rope, tents, aircraft tires and parachutes.
<p>
   It also served to improve British-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> relations, in a way.
Young American soldiers stationed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Britain</ENAMEX> made a good impression
on their dates by giving them nylon stockings, available from the
military's post exchanges when they could not be bought elsewhere.
<p>
   The reintroduction of nylon to civilian life after the war
caused a sensation, and at least one stampede. A crowd of 10,000
people jammed a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">San Francisco</ENAMEX> department store in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1945</TIMEX>, causing the
nylon sale to be called off.
<p>
   In the decades since, nylon has become ubiquitous, as carpeting
and clothing. And about two-thirds of all the luggage manufactured
in the world is made from it.
<p>
   Scientists consider nylon a benign product of technology,
because it has not been found to have any deadly side effects. But
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX>, who loved wildlife and was a dedicated bird-watcher, said in
a <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1988</TIMEX> interview that he thought ``the human race is going to
perish by being smothered in plastic.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Julian Werner Hill</ENAMEX> was born in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">St. Louis</ENAMEX>, graduated from
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Washington University</ENAMEX> there in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1924</TIMEX> and earned a doctorate in
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1928</TIMEX>. His wife recalled on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> that his doctoral studies were
delayed a year because he was stricken with scarlet fever.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> played the violin and was an accomplished squash player and
figure-skater until his early 40s, when an attack of polio weakened
one leg, his wife said.
<p>
   Before his retirement from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Du Pont</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1964</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hill</ENAMEX> supervised the
company's program of aid to universities for research in physics
and chemistry.
<p>
   Surviving besides his wife are a daughter, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Louisa Spottswood</ENAMEX> of
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Philadelphia</ENAMEX>; two sons, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Joseph</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Villanova</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pa.</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jefferson</ENAMEX>,
of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, and five grandchildren.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">01-31-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1910EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960207.0657 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=f pri=r> A6958 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tia-z> BC-DOMINICAN-AIR-CRASH-U </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-07</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0674 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-DOMINICAN-AIR-CRASH-UPDATE2-BLOOM
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">BOEING</ENAMEX> AIRLINER CRASHES IN <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CARIBBEAN</ENAMEX> WITH 189 ABOARD (UPDATE2)
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Molinski</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bloomberg Business News</ENAMEX>
   (Updates with latest body total, no survivors found; adds that
search was called off for the night, with in second and third
paragraphs; adds report that lightning stuck the craft, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">German
Foreign Ministry</ENAMEX> comment response, in seventh paragraph.)
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santo Domingo</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>, <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 7</TIMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bloomberg</ENAMEX>) -- A
chartered <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 carrying German tourists from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican
Republic</ENAMEX> crashed into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION" MIN="Caribbean">Caribbean sea</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">last night</TIMEX>, leaving no sign
that any of the 189 people on board survived.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Coast Guard</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> said it recovered 79 bodies in the
area of the crash, before suspending its search at nightfall <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">today</TIMEX>.
It plans to continue the search in the <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">morning</TIMEX>.
<p>
   ``We'll continue searching until there is reason to believe
there are no survivors,'' said Petty Officer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Scott Carr</ENAMEX>, a
spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coast Guard</ENAMEX>, <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">this evening</TIMEX>. ``We still maintain
hope that somebody is out there and we will try to find them.''
<p>
   Searchers did find some life rafts, but no survivors, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coast
Guard</ENAMEX> said. It wasn't clear whether the rafts were dragged out by
survivors or if they inflated on impact.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> officials said the cause of the
crash was unknown. The owner of the German tour agency that
chartered the plane was quoted by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX> as saying lightning
struck the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX>-bound 757.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Vural Oeger</ENAMEX>, head of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hamburg</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oeger Tours</ENAMEX>, said he was told
by Dominican aviation officials that the plane's engines were
damaged by lightning. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX> also said the pilots apparently tried
to turn the plane around to return to the airport, but were unable
to and plunged into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   A spokeswoman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">German Foreign Ministry</ENAMEX> said that while
she'd heard rumors of lightning causing the wreck, she couldn't
confirm the reports.
<p>
   The plane crashed just before <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">midnight local time</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last night</TIMEX>,
about five minutes after taking off from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX> airport
in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coast Guard</ENAMEX> officials said rain and
sharks were hampering the rescue efforts.
<p>
   A spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing Co.</ENAMEX> said it was sending
a team to help investigate the crash.
<p>
   The aircraft, owned by Turkish company <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgen Air</ENAMEX>, was leased to
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alas de Transporte Internacional</ENAMEX>, a Dominican charter airline that
operates mainly during the peak winter season when European
tourists visit the resort town of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX>, said a spokeswoman
for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Aeronautica Civil</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>'s aviation agency.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON|ORGANIZATION">Oeger</ENAMEX> had chartered the plane from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alas</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The aircraft, built in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1985</TIMEX>, carried 176 passengers, most of
them German tourists, and 13 crew members -- 11 Turkish nationals
and two Dominicans.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Russ Young</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> spokesman, said the investigation could
last weeks or months.
<p>
   The jet was the 31st <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 made and was originally sold to
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern Air Lines</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX>, which became a subsidiary of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Texas Air
Corp.</ENAMEX> after filing for bankruptcy in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1989</TIMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Martin Brodie</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls-Royce Plc</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>, said
the plane was fitted with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls-Royce</ENAMEX> RB211-535 engines. He said
the power plant was ``one of the most reliable engines in
service.''
<p>
   The company had no idea yet what went wrong and there was no
immediate evidence that the engines were to blame.
<p>
   The crash was the second of a 757 in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">less than two months</TIMEX>. On
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Dec. 20</TIMEX>, an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines</ENAMEX> jet crashed in the mountains near
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cali</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX>, killing 160 of the 164 people on board. The cause
of that crash is still under investigation.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>, which shares the island of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hispaniola</ENAMEX>
with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Haiti</ENAMEX>, is the most popular <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX> destination for Germans.
Hundreds of thousands of German tourists visit the island each
year, attracted by its low prices and tropical beaches.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oeger</ENAMEX> is one of a number of discount tour agencies in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>
which charters planes to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-07-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2013EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960208.0062 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=i pri=u> A7267 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-DOMINICAN-CRASH-ART-2 </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-08</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0877 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-DOMINICAN-CRASH-ART-2NDLD-WRITETHRU-650&AMP;ADD-NYT
(Subs 1st graf to update number of bodies recovered)
GERMAN TOURIST PLANE CRASHES; 189 FEARED DEAD
(ART ADV: Graphic and locator-map have been sent to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NYT</ENAMEX> graphic
212-556-4204 or 1927.)
(JT)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX> 
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX> 
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 carrying 189 people, mostly tourists
on their way home to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Berlin</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican
Republic</ENAMEX>, crashed into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">late Tuesday</TIMEX> about 13 miles
offshore. At least 105 bodies were recovered, American officials
said.
<p>
   Debris was spread in an area two miles long and 150 yards wide,
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United States Coast Guard</ENAMEX> said, suggesting that the jet broke
up before it hit the water.
<p>
   But an official at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">German Embassy</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santo Domingo</ENAMEX>, the
capital of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>, said the fuel had not caught
fire, indicating that the plane had not exploded.
<p>
   The official, the first secretary at the embassy, said bad
weather was likely the cause.
<p>
   ``More than <NUMEX TYPE="PERCENT">50 percent</NUMEX>, it was the interference of bad
weather,'' the official, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Klaus D. Brock</ENAMEX>, said in a telephone
interview. The plane had taken off from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX>, about 100
miles northwest of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Santo Domingo</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The crash was the second recent loss of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 in flight:
In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">December</TIMEX> a 757 crashed near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cali</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX>; pilot error appears
to have been the primary cause.
<p>
   Aviation officials in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX> gave conflicting information
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX> about the flight, which reached an altitude of about
7,000 feet before crashing.
<p>
   Gen. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hector Ramon</ENAMEX>, head of the civil aviation agency, said the
pilot had radioed the tower that he had a problem and was
returning, news reports said. But Maj. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Emmanuel Souffront</ENAMEX>, of the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominican Air Force</ENAMEX>, said a transcript of radio communication with
air traffic controllers indicated there had not been a problem.
<p>
   ``The aircraft started to turn to the right and disappeared from
the radar screen,'' he was quoted as saying.
<p>
   ``Before it went down, someone radioed from the aircraft, `Stand
by.'''
<p>
   In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Berlin</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX>, friends and family of the passengers
arrived at the airports to find flags flying at half staff and
teams of doctors, psychologists and clergy to meet them.
<p>
   The 11-year-old plane, originally built for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Eastern Air Lines</ENAMEX>,
was owned by a Turkish company and under lease, with a crew, to a
Dominican airline, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alas de Transporte Internacional</ENAMEX>, for a single
flight. It carried 176 passengers, including 4 children. Eleven of
the crew were Turkish and two Dominican.
<p>
   The Turkish company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgen Air</ENAMEX>, was using the plane to fill a
charter commitment to a German company, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Oger Tours</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hamburg</ENAMEX>.
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Wolfgang Schwalm</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Frankfurt</ENAMEX> airport, said the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 had replaced a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 767 at the last minute because the
767 had technical problems.
<p>
   In <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Istanbul</ENAMEX>, the general manager of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgen</ENAMEX> said on television
that he believed the plane had been hit by lightning. But the jet
is designed to withstand any such strikes.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United States Coast Guard</ENAMEX> dispatched three cutters to help
retrieve bodies. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX> sent two civil aviation officials and
three officials from the federal police in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Weisbaden</ENAMEX> to help
identify bodies.
<p>
to assist investigators, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Transportation Safety
Board</ENAMEX> said it would send investigators if more evidence became
available.
<p>
   But it was not clear who would pay to retrieve the plane's data
recorder from the wreckage, off the north coast of the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican
Republic</ENAMEX> where the water is about 3,000 feet deep. Retrieval could
cost <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">hundreds of thousands of dollars</NUMEX>. Though the plane was
American built, neither it nor the airline nor the flight was under
American jurisdiction, and no Americans were on board.
<p>
   Nevertheless, American safety experts said they would be very
interested in learning more about the crash if it was caused by
mechanical problems or by weather.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-08-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">0216EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>

<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960208.0763 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=i pri=u> A8248 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-DOMINICAN-CRASH-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-08</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-DOMINICAN-CRASH-NYT
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX> TO HUNT FOR BLACK BOX FROM AIR CRASH
(HLW)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">UPPER MARLBORO</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Md.</ENAMEX>  &MD;  The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said here on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> that it had
shipped equipment to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> to help find the flight
data recorder of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 that crashed offshore on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Tuesday</TIMEX>
<TIMEX TYPE="TIME">night</TIMEX>, killing all 189 people on board.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials said they had been asked to locate the so-called
black box, but so far have not been asked to help retrieve it or
any other parts of the wreckage. In the meantime, discussions
continued about who would pay to salvage parts of the jet.
<p>
   The Turkish-owned charter jet, which was leased to a Dominican
airline, was carrying German tourists home from a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Caribbean</ENAMEX>
vacation when it plunged into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic</ENAMEX> shortly after takeoff
from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX> in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Late on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">afternoon</TIMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Puerto Plata</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Coast Guard</ENAMEX> said
it had given up its search, and it remained uncertain exactly how
many bodies had been accounted for.
<p>
   Dominican officials said 128 bodies had been recovered. A
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> spokesman said local people in boats appeared to have
stripped some bodies of money and identification.
<p>
   After the crash, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX> asked for help from the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Capt. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Raymond Scott McCord</ENAMEX>, supervisor of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>'s salvage and
diving operations, said at a briefing here on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> that the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 went down in an area where the water is from 1,000 feet
to 13,000 feet deep, with the sea bottom flat in some parts and
jagged in others.
<p>
   Although <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">McCord</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> had retrieved wreckage in more
challenging places, he declined to predict the likelihood of
success in recovering the black box in this case, or what it would
cost.
<p>
   The black boxes on passenger jets are equipped with metal
cylinders that emit a ``ping'' sound when immersed in water.
<p>
   So far, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> has sent a Towed Ping Locator System, also
known as a tow fish, to the area. The device is pulled on a cable,
about 2,500 feet above the ocean floor, at 2 to 3 knots, and,
depending on water conditions, it can hear the pinger on the black
box at a distance of up to a mile.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials and aviation experts plan to review air traffic
control radar and other data in an effort to narrow the search
area. When they finish, probably on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Tuesday</TIMEX> or <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Wednesday</TIMEX>, they will
begin surveying the ocean, he said.
<p>
   ``Looking for anything on the ocean floor is very difficult,
because you are working blind,'' he said. ``The analogy is a needle
in a haystack. But with a pinger locator, you know which side of
the haystack you're looking at.''
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> also showed off a bigger robot probe that would carry
out the next step, making sonar maps of the bottom, to locate the
debris fields. A third remote-controlled device, with video and
still cameras and manipulator arms, would then be sent down. All
three are towed by a ship, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> is now negotiating with
commercial ship owners for a suitable vessel, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">McCord</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   No one would say what such an operation would cost.
<p>
spokesman, said, ``any costs are expected to be incurred on a
cost-sharing basis.''
<p>
   ``We certainly have a strong interest in that aircraft; it's our
aircraft,'' he said.
<p>
   ``There are others who have an equally strong interest,'' he
said, citing ``countries and corporate entities.'' These would
apparently include <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Germany</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Turkey</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dominican Republic</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX>,
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alas de Transporte Internacional</ENAMEX>, which leased the plane, and
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Birgenair</ENAMEX>, a small Turkish company that owned the plane and
provided the crew.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-08-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2101EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960214.0765 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=r> A4505 </STORYID>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-14</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0535 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
of raw data.''
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-14-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2111EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960215.0294 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=f pri=r> A4985 </STORYID>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-15</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0944 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CHINA</ENAMEX>-SATELLITE-BLOOM
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">HUGHES</ENAMEX> DELAYS <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CHINA</ENAMEX> SATELLITE SHIPMENT AFTER EXPLOSION (UPDATE1)
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients)
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bloomberg Business News</ENAMEX>
   (Updates with additional information about future launches,
crash failure.)
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beijing</ENAMEX>, <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 15</TIMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bloomberg</ENAMEX>) -- <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hughes Aircraft Corp.</ENAMEX>, the
satellite-making arm of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Motors</ENAMEX>, delayed shipment of a new
satellite to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> after <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">this morning</TIMEX>'s launch failure by a Chinese
rocket, a company official said.
<p>
   ``It's been delayed,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">K.C. Lang</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hughes</ENAMEX> executive in
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beijing</ENAMEX>. ``It's been held off and we don't know when it's coming.''
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">This morning</TIMEX>'s launch failure, in which a rocket exploded
shortly after lifting off, cast doubt on whether <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> will be able
to complete an ambitious schedule of satellite launches.
<p>
   ``There may be adjustments to our future plans because of the
accident,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Zhang Lihui</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for the rocketmaker,
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Great Wall Industry Corp.</ENAMEX> ``I can't tell you anything about
the possible changes now.''
<p>
   The next launch -- of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hughes</ENAMEX>-built Apstar-1A communications
satellite -- is scheduled for <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">mid-March</TIMEX> aboard a Long March 3
rocket built by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Great Wall</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The customer is the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">APT Satellite Co.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX>, whose
shareholders include commercial arms of the Chinese army, space and
telecommunications authorities, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore Telecom</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Thailand</ENAMEX>'s
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Charoen Pokhpand Group</ENAMEX>.
<p>
as it was being launched just after <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">3.00 a.m.</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">today</TIMEX>, showering
debris on the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Xichang</ENAMEX> launch site in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION" MIN="China">southwest China</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Sichuan</ENAMEX>
province.
<p>
   The rocket apparently exploded after rising just a few hundred
feet from its launch pad, crashing down on a road one mile away.
There are no reports of injuries.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Great Wall</ENAMEX> officials in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beijing</ENAMEX> said company executives
are locked in discussions in the capital and at the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Xichang</ENAMEX> space
base to determine what went wrong.
<p>
   It was the first launch for the heavy payload-carrying Long
March 3-B vehicle, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Great Wall</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Zhang Xiaolin</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   Clean-up operations to contain the spillage of hazardous
chemical wastes have begun. Numerous calls to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Xichang</ENAMEX> failed to
reach any officials.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX>'s satellite launch track record has been patchy. In
flight, destroying the Apstar-2 satellite it carried.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> competes with American, European and Russian launchers on
the basis of price.
<p>
   An agreement <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last year</TIMEX> between <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beijing</ENAMEX> was to
have curtailed Chinese price cutting to a maximum of <NUMEX TYPE="PERCENT">10 percent</NUMEX>
under <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> launch costs for proven vehicles.
<p>
   ``If the launch is successful, it will be terrific,'' the
official <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Beijing Youth Daily</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">yesterday</TIMEX> quoted <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Great Wall</ENAMEX>
senior engineer <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Long Lehou</ENAMEX> as saying. ``However, if it fails, the
consequences will be disastrous.''
<p>
   The failure delivered a blow to a group including <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rupert
use the spacecraft to beam television signals to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Latin America</ENAMEX>. The
satellite was built by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Loral Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intelsat</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The explosion is likely to raise the cost of insuring future
launches, analysts said. <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Shanghai</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Pacific Insurance Co.</ENAMEX>
on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Monday</TIMEX>, the official <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Daily</ENAMEX> reported <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Tuesday</TIMEX>.
<p>
   ``Maybe the insurance policies will increase a lot for the Long
March family,'' said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Li Ming</ENAMEX>, chief of the international business
department at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">China Pacific Insurance</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   The 2-E and the untested 3-B versions of the Long March rockets
are considered by foreign analysts to be less reliable than the
Long March 3, which has had only one failure in more than 20
launches.
<p>
   The 2-E rockets are used to propel satellites into low orbits of
about 200 kilometers above the planet, while the 3-series rockets
can enable satellites to reach orbits out to 35,000 kilometers.
<p>
   This was to have been <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX>'s busiest year of satellite
launches.
<p>
   After <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">next month</TIMEX>'s planned launch, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> plans to launch another
of its DongFangHong3 satellites on a Long March 3-A rocket in by
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">May</TIMEX>.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">May</TIMEX> or <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">June</TIMEX>, a satellite for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EchoStar
Communications Corp.</ENAMEX> is due to be launched on a Long March 2-E.
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Last December</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> successfully launched an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Echostar</ENAMEX> satellite
from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Xichang</ENAMEX>, the most recent Chinese success.
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">July</TIMEX>, a Long March 3 rocket is to scheduled to carry a
company. The satellite is to be built by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hughes Aircraft Co.</ENAMEX>
<p>
   In <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">July-August</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">China</ENAMEX> plans to launch a recoverable spy
supplied by <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Loral Corp.</ENAMEX>
--<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Peter Hannam</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Beijing</ENAMEX> (8610) 532-4492 with reporting by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Alec
D.B. McCabe</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Shanghai</ENAMEX> (8621) 6255-2634 through the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX>
newsroom (852) 2521-4500 jh
<p>
of shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">GM</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Intelsat</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">TCI</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Televisa</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">News Corp.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Singapore
Telecom</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Charoen Pokhpand</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philippine Long Distance</ENAMEX>: GM, 2237Z US,
TCOMA US, TV US, NWS US, ST SP, CPF TB, TEL PM Equity &QR;  GP. For
more news, replace GP with BQ. For more NI
codes: MED for more industry news; <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">CHINA</ENAMEX>; HK for <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hong Kong</ENAMEX>; LDC for
emerging markets; ASIAX for Asian news excluding <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New Zealand</ENAMEX>
and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Australia</ENAMEX>.) -0- ( -0- (BBN) <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb/15/96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">17:34</TIMEX> EOS (BBN) <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb/15/96</TIMEX>
<TIMEX TYPE="TIME">03:34</TIMEX> 86
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-15-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">0524EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960222.0269 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=f pri=r> A2555 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tia-z> BC-F14-CRASHES-BLOOM </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-F14-CRASHES-BLOOM
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NORTHROP GRUMMAN</ENAMEX> F-14S TO STAND DOWN FOR REVIEW OF ACCIDENTS
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bill Arthur</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Washington</ENAMEX>, <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 22</TIMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bloomberg</ENAMEX>) -- The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> ordered its <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop
Grumman Corp.</ENAMEX> F-14s out of the skies for three days while it
investigates three recent F-14 crashes.
<p>
   The action came after an F-14A fighter crashed <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">today</TIMEX> in the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX>. The two crew members ejected and were rescued and
returned to the aircraft carrier USS Nimitz with minor injuries,
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Sunday</TIMEX>, an F-14D crashed into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pacific Ocean</ENAMEX> off <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION" MIN="California">southern
California</ENAMEX>, killing its two crew members. And on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Jan. 29</TIMEX>, an F-14A
crashed into houses in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tennessee</ENAMEX>, after takeoff, killing
the two crew members and three people on the ground.
<p>
   The cause of <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">today</TIMEX>'s crash is undetermined.
<p>
   ``In light of the recent mishaps involving F-14As and Ds, the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> has ordered a 72-hour safety standdown for all F-14
aircraft,'' said Lt. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Greg Geisen</ENAMEX>, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> spokesman at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   ``Although different models of the F-14 have been involved in
these mishaps, it is prudent to temporarily suspend routine flight
operations for all F-14s in order to assess the available
information and determine if procedural or other modifications to
F-14 operations are warranted,'' the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   A one-time exception to the standdown will be allowed for 14
F-14s on board the USS America, which is returning to the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United
States</ENAMEX> from the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bosnia</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geisen</ENAMEX> said. Those planes
will be permitted to fly to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Oceana Naval Air Station</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Virginia</ENAMEX>, as
the ship nears port.
<p>
   The F14 ``Tomcat'' is the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>'s first-line fighter aircraft. It
has two-engines and is capable of action in all weather, day or
night. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> has about 330 F-14s in three models, As, Bs and Ds.
<p>
   The models differ mainly in engines and avionics. The A model
uses engines from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pratt &AMP; Whitney</ENAMEX>, a unit of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">United Technologies
Corp.</ENAMEX> The B and D models use <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">General Electric</ENAMEX> engines.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said there have been F-14 32 crashes since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX>. That
figure isn't uncommon for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> jet fighter aircraft, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geisen</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   The aircraft was introduced to the fleet in the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">mid 1970s</TIMEX>, and
has undergone several upgrades since then, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geisen</ENAMEX> said. The planes
were made by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Grumman Corp.</ENAMEX>, now <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop Grumman</ENAMEX>, principally in
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calverton</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX>, on <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Long Island</ENAMEX>. The company delivered the last
F-14 to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1992</TIMEX>, said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop Grumman</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John
Vosilla</ENAMEX>. He referred all questions about <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">today</TIMEX>'s crash to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   Aviation safety and engineering experts will review the data
from the three recent crashes and are to present their findings to
the Chief of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Naval Operations</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mike Boorda</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">in three days</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Geisen</ENAMEX>
said.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop Grumman</ENAMEX> shares were up 3/8 to 66 1/4 at <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">midday</TIMEX>.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1221EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960222.0558 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=w pri=u> A3160 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tdt-z> BC-GROUNDED-JETS-BOS </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-GROUNDED-JETS-BOS
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX> GROUNDS F-14'S AFTER THIRD RECENT CRASH
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">CHRIS BLACK</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">The Boston Globe</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> suspended operations for its entire fleet
of F-14 airplanes <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> after the third ``Tomcat'' crash in a
month  &MD;  the second in a week.
<p>
   The 72-hour ``safety stand-down'' came shortly after an F-14
fighter from the USS Nimitz crashed during flight operations in the
northern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX> at about <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">6:30 a.m. EST</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> announced that the two Naval aviators on board were
rescued by a SH-60 helicopter after they ejected from the aircraft.
The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said that both men were in good condition. One aviator
suffered minor abrasions. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> is investigating the cause.
<p>
   Another Tomcat crashed off the coast of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX> during
exercises on the aircraft carrier Carl Vinson on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Sunday</TIMEX>. Both crew
members were killed. <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Late last month</TIMEX>, an F-14 crashed near
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashville</ENAMEX>, killing both crew members and three civilians on the
ground.
<p>
   Although the crash <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> was the third Tomcat crash <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this
year</TIMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Defense Department</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kenneth Bacon</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> had
uncovered no evidence of a flaw in the aircraft.
<p>
   A safety stand-down is a procedure the military uses to conduct
an intensive review. During this three-day period, the three
classes of F-14s will stay out of the air so <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> personnel can
review maintenance procedures and equipment, plus check each
aircraft for weaknesses or deficiencies.
<p>
   The F-14s on the deck of the USS America will be allowed to fly
off because the aircraft carrier is returning from a deployment.
Carrier decks are routinely cleared of aircraft the day before the
carrier docks.
<p>
   ``We do not know what has caused these three crashes <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this
year</TIMEX>,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bacon</ENAMEX> said. ``The goal of the stand-down is to take a time
out to look at everything involved with the F-14s.
<p>
   Adm. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeremy Boorda</ENAMEX>, the chief of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Naval Operations</ENAMEX>, informed
Deputy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Defense</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John White</ENAMEX> of the latest crash <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX>
<TIMEX TYPE="TIME">morning</TIMEX> and told him he was ordering the standdown for the entire
fleet of more than 300 aircraft, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bacon</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   ``What the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> is trying to do is find out what caused these
accidents,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bacon</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
    &UR;  &LR; In the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">past five years</TIMEX>, 32 F-14s have crashed. One of the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>'s first female pilots, Lt. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kara Hultgren</ENAMEX>, died while trying to
land an F-14 on an aircraft carrier in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1994</TIMEX>. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> concluded
that engine failure caused that crash.
<p>
   The Tomcat, a <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$38 million</NUMEX>, twin-engine aircraft built by the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Grumman Aerospace Corp.</ENAMEX>, is the standard fighter plane used by the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> for close-in air combat. The aircraft has been in operation
since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1973</TIMEX>. The oldest version of the aircraft, the F-14A, is
scheduled to be phased out by the year <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">2004</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The crash rate for the F-14 dropped dramatically after the
initial years of deployment and has generally gone down since then
except for occasional spurts of accidents, according to Naval
records.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bacon</ENAMEX> said the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> had no single explanation for the increases
in F-14 accidents.
<p>
   ``The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> informs me that they have been unable to find a
common thread to these accidents,'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bacon</ENAMEX> said. ``This is a
mystery.''
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1924EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960222.0660 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A3300 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-F14-CRASH-ART-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-F14-CRASH-ART-NYT
AFTER SERIES OF CRASHES, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX> GROUNDS ITS F-14S
(ART ADV.: Graphic for use with this story is being sent to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NYT</ENAMEX>
graphics clients. Non-subscribers may make individual purchase by
calling 212 556-4204.)
(HLW)
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Navy</ENAMEX> ordered all of its F-14s out of the
skies for at least three days after one of them crashed on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX>
in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX>, the third crash of an F-14 in the last month.
<p>
   The two-man crew survived the crash, ejecting into the northern
waters of the gulf, and were rescued and returned to the carrier
Nimitz.
<p>
   The two crewmen, who were not identified, were reported to have
suffered minor injuries.
<p>
   The three-day shutdown of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>'s fleet of more than 330
F-14s was ordered by the chief of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">naval operations</ENAMEX>, Adm. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeremy M.
Boorda</ENAMEX>, who said in an interview at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pentagon</ENAMEX> that while there
was no immediate evidence of a connection among the three crashes,
``This is an airplane that we worry about.''
<p>
   ``A jinxed airplane?'' he said. ``No. But known deficiencies in
the earlier models? Yes, and we're working on that, including some
changes to the aircraft.''
<p>
   He said the three-day review might result in new restrictions on
use of the plane, nicknamed the Tomcat, which has the highest
accident rate for jet fighters in the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> fleet. Ten F-14s have
gone down in the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">past two years</TIMEX>, and 32 since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX>. Each plane
costs more than <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$30 million</NUMEX>.
<p>
   ``We may come out with some more operational restrictions, but
it's way too early to say that,'' the admiral said. ``This is too
serious a business to be guessing about.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials said that during the shutdown, special engineers
and other safety experts would review the evidence available from
the three recent crashes and inspect the rest of the fleet for
defects in the planes, in their maintenance, or in pilot training.
<p>
   Earlier models of the fighter, called the F-14A, were plagued
with engine problems when they entered the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>'s fleet of
carrier-based jet fighters in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1973</TIMEX>. Specifically, the engines used
on the first model were not powerful enough for a fighter of its
size.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> was forced to impose strict restrictions on how pilots
could operate the aircraft, and had to replace many of the engines.
Two of the three planes that have crashed since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">late January</TIMEX> were
F-14As.
<p>
   The engines installed in later models, the F-14B and the F-14D,
were more powerful and have proved more reliable. Despite the
troubles of the F-14 fleet, the rate of accidents among all <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>
fighter planes has come down dramatically in recent years, a record
that has made the recent spate of crashes all the more alarming.
<p>
   In the first of the crashes <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">this year</TIMEX>, an F-14A crashed into a
residential neighborhood in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tenn.</ENAMEX>, on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Jan. 29</TIMEX>, seconds
after takeoff. The two-man crew was killed, along with three people
on the ground. The pilot was involved in another F-14 crash in
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1995</TIMEX>.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Last Sunday</TIMEX>, the crew of an F-14D was killed when the fighter
plunged into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pacific</ENAMEX> off the coast of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Southern California</ENAMEX>
during exercises.
<p>
   The F-14 that crashed on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> had flown from the Nimitz,
which is sailing in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX> to enforce a no-fly zone over
southern <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Iraq</ENAMEX>, an operation that dates from the end of the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX> war
in the gulf. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials said that the plane was on a routine
training mission. They would not speculate on the cause of the
crash.
<p>
   The plane, which was manufacutred by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Grumman Corp.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Long
Island</ENAMEX>, has gone out of production, and the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> has begun to phase
out the plane entirely, replacing it with the F-18.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2131EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960222.0661 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A3301 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">COLOMBIA</ENAMEX>-AIRCRASH-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0719 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">COLOMBIA</ENAMEX>-AIRCRASH-NYT
(EXCLUSIVE; <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">10 p.m. ET</TIMEX> EMBARGO)
JET THAT CRASHED IN <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">COLOMBIA</ENAMEX> REPORTEDLY STRIPPED OF PARTS
(HLW)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  Scavengers have descended on the wreckage of the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines</ENAMEX> jetliner that crashed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last December</TIMEX>,
making off with more than 500 parts, including the jet engines, the
landing gear, and electronic components for possible sale to other
carriers, the airline said.
<p>
   A spokesman for the airline said that to its knowledge, no parts
of the plane had yet been offered for sale, and on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX> the
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Aviation Administration</ENAMEX> said it was notifying other
airlines of the possibility.
<p>
   Not long after the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757 jetliner crashed <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last Dec. 20</TIMEX> in a
remote mountain area near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Buga</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Colombia</ENAMEX>, killing 160 of the 164
people on board, the Colombian authorities said people were taking
valuables from the bodies of the dead passengers as well as the
luggage.
<p>
   <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Last month</TIMEX>, the airline sent other airlines and aviation
companies an 11-page list of the missing parts and their serial
numbers along with a letter warning: ``These parts could pose a
significant safety risk should they be installed on other aircraft
since they were involved in a crash.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Hotard</ENAMEX>, a spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX>, said by telephone: ``You
may have a part that looks perfectly good on the outside, but if
you get into some of the sophisticated testing, you may find out
it's not good.''
<p>
   Although the plane was a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 757, flying from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Miami</ENAMEX> to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Cali</ENAMEX>,
many of the parts would also fit a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 767.
<p>
   The airline's letter, first reported in The Cleveland Plain
Dealer, noted: ``Any part taken from the crash site and/or offered
for sale without the express written approval of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Airlines
Inc.</ENAMEX>, should be considered a stolen aircraft part.'' It cited
sections of federal law that made such activity illegal and
threatened that any supplier caught handling any of the parts would
be barred from doing business with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX>.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hotard</ENAMEX> said that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX> was not interested in the salvage
value of the parts but that some could be sold for a lot of money
if passed off as being in good condition. Testifying before a
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Senate</ENAMEX> aviation subcommittee <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last June</TIMEX>, federal investigators said
various small parts of airplanes that are worth <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">hundreds of dollars</NUMEX>
in new condition, are available for a few dollars from scrap
dealers in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> and may find their way back into
airplanes, although the parts are not suitable.
<p>
   The local Colombian authorities did retrieve the black boxes
with cockpit voice and flight data recordings, and technicians at
analyzed them. The safety board and the Colombian authorities
recently said there did not appear to be any mechanical problem
with the plane before the crash.
<p>
   That means that the stolen parts would probably not be useful in
determining the cause of this crash. In some other crashes,
investigators have sorted through tons of debris to find components
that offer clues.
<p>
   Stealing parts from crash scenes is not new. When a Colombian
DC-8 cargo plane crashed on <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 5</TIMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Asuncion</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paraguay</ENAMEX>, killing
23 people, local television showed a man stealing engine parts from
the debris, The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Associated Press</ENAMEX> reported. In the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX>,
crash scenes are usually cordoned off, in part to protect the
evidence and to prevent the spread of blood-borne infection.
<p>
   A spokesman for the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing Co.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Richard F. Schleh</ENAMEX>, said the
company had helped <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX> distribute its letter, which he
described as ``a very good precautionary effort.''
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Margaret Gilligan</ENAMEX>, the deputy associate administrator for
regulation and certification at the aviation agency, said the
agency did not believe that parts had been stolen from planes that
had crashed in this country, but she said the agency did not know
what happened abroad.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">William A. Machado</ENAMEX>, who heads an <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">FAA</ENAMEX> program to investigate
aircraft parts that are counterfeit or come from unapproved
suppliers, said of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American</ENAMEX> letter: ``It's the first time I've
seen it, but I can understand their concern, because they really
didn't have a lot of control.'' <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Machado</ENAMEX> called the letter ``a
responsible action on their part.''
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-22-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2132EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960224.0155 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A4844 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX>-JET-CRASHES-NYT </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-24</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX>-JET-CRASHES-NYT
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NAVY</ENAMEX> RESTRICTS FLIGHTS OF TROUBLE-PLAGUED F-14
(kd)
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> imposed new restrictions <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Saturday</TIMEX> on
pilots who fly the F-14 jet fighter, after three of the
trouble-plagued jets crashed in the last month, killing four <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>
airmen and three civilians.
<p>
   While the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said it had found no common thread in the recent
crashes, it announced that it had placed temporary limitations on
the speed at which F-14s could be flown, and on the use of
afterburners, which give a plane extra thrust by injecting fuel
into hot exhaust gases.
<p>
   All F-14 pilots will also be required to undergo refresher
safety courses before they are allowed to fly again, a requirement
that could keep some grounded for several more days.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> made the announcement as it ended a three-day worldwide
shutdown on operations of the carrier-based F-14 Tomcat.
<p>
   In recent years the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX>'s fleet of more than 330 F-14s has
suffered a series of catastrophic accidents, including a crash on
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Jan. 29</TIMEX> in which one of the early models of the fighter, an F-14A,
smashed into a residential neighborhood in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashville</ENAMEX>, killing the
two-man crew and three civilians on the ground.
<p>
   On <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Feb. 18</TIMEX>, one of the latest models, an F-14D, went down off
the coast of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">southern California</ENAMEX>, killing its two-person crew.
<p>
   On <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX>, an F-14A crashed into the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Persian Gulf</ENAMEX>; the pilot
and radar operator survived with only minor injuries.
<p>
   The F-14 has the highest accident rate among <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> combat planes,
and its problems have mounted even as the overall safety record for
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> planes has improved dramatically in recent years. Ten F-14s
have gone down in the <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">past two years</TIMEX>, and 32 since <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1991</TIMEX>. Each plane
costs more than <NUMEX TYPE="MONEY">$30 million</NUMEX>.
<p>
   In announcing the three-day halt to operations <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last week</TIMEX>, the
Chief of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Naval Operations</ENAMEX>, Adm. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jeremy M. Boorda</ENAMEX>, said that the
F-14 was ``an airplane that we worry about.'' Earlier models of the
plane had engines that were not powerful enough for a fighter of
its size, which led to restrictions on their use and, in some
cases, replacement of the engine.
<p>
   In a statement <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Saturday</TIMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said that the new restrictions
on speed and on the use of afterburners would remain in effect
until the investigations of the three recent crashes had ended. The
statement did not rule out permanent restrictions in the future.
<p>
   ``It should be emphasized that the investigations continue to
determine causes and any permanent corrective action required,''
the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> said. ``The requirements and limitations placed in effect
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">today</TIMEX> are intended to permit safe operation of the F-14 aircraft
pending completion of the investigations.''
<p>
   Under the restrictions, F-14 fighters cannot fly more than 550
nautical miles an hour, below an altitude of 10,000 feet.
Restrictions on the use of afterburners apply to later models of
the plane.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials said <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Saturday</TIMEX> that the restrictions would not
affect the plane's usefulness, since the limitations would be
immediately waived in combat. ``If a pilot is out there and needs
to fly his airplane, he's going to fly his airplane as he needs
to,'' said a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> spokesman.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House National Security Committee</ENAMEX> has announced that
hearings would be held <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">next week</TIMEX> on the safety record of the F-14.
The panel is expected to hear testimony from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> officials, pilots
and representatives of the manufacturer, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Grumman Corp.</ENAMEX>, which
merged with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Northrop</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1994</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The two <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">House</ENAMEX> Republicans who are sponsoring the hearings,
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Duncan Hunter</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Randy Cunningham</ENAMEX>, both from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">California</ENAMEX>, said in a
statement that ``too many lives and too much equipment has been
lost'' in F-14 crashes. Although the plane's problems precede the
<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Clinton</ENAMEX> administration by many years, the lawmakers said that they
planned to investigate whether the administration ``is underfunding
both the readiness and modernization of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Navy</ENAMEX> aircraft.''
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-24-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">1657EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960227.0636 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=r> A7779 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=tth-z> BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX>-CRASH-SPI </SLUG>
<DATE> &LR; </DATE>
<NWORDS> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-27</TIMEX> </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX>-CRASH-SPI
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> TESTS BORROWED 737 IN CRASH PROBE
(For use by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Times News Service</ENAMEX> clients.)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">BILL VIRGIN</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Seattle Post-Intelligencer</ENAMEX>
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 737 from <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX>'s <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Museum of Flight</ENAMEX> as part of its
investigation into why a similar jetliner crashed near <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX>
in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1994</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The museum's aircraft, ironically enough, was donated by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USAir</ENAMEX>,
which operated the airplane that crashed, killing 132 people on
board.
<p>
   The board is testing the plane's rudder controls to learn why
Flight 427 suddenly rolled and crashed while on its approach to the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> airport <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Sept. 8, 1994</TIMEX>. Aviation safety investigators say
a sharp movement of the rudder  &MD;  the movable vertical piece in the
plane's tail  &MD;  could have caused the jet's deadly roll.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> Chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jim Hall</ENAMEX> is to address a briefing on the
investigation in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">Thursday</TIMEX>, but board spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Mike Benson</ENAMEX>
said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Hall</ENAMEX> isn't expected to announce any findings.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Benson</ENAMEX> said investigators are simulating air loads on the 737's
rudder. ``It's a slow, methodical job since we don't have adequate
black boxes,'' he said.
<p>
   Newer models of flight data recorders, or ``black boxes,'' would
record the angle of the rudder and the pedal controlling it. But
because the plane was reduced to debris by the force of the crash,
and the 737 was equipped with older-model flight recorders that
didn't measure such information, investigators are running tests to
``surmise'' rudder and pedal position, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Benson</ENAMEX> said.
<p>
   Installation of improved flight recorders was an official
recommendation of the board after earlier hearings into the
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> crash.
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Museum of Flight</ENAMEX> spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bill Hayes</ENAMEX> said the plane, donated
<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last September</TIMEX>, was to be partially dismantled as an exhibit. The
<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> was looking for an intact plane on which to conduct tests, so
the museum delayed its plans.
<p>
   The tests are being conducted at a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> hangar at <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Boeing
Field</ENAMEX>. No airborne tests are planned.
<p>
   The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NTSB</ENAMEX> also conducted tests <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">last September</TIMEX> to determine if
wake turbulence from another plane could have contributed to the
crash. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Benson</ENAMEX> said those results are still being analyzed.
</TEXT>
<TRAILER>
NYT-<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">02-27-96</TIMEX> <TIMEX TYPE="TIME">2052EST</TIMEX>
</TRAILER>
</DOC>
<DOC>
<DOCID> nyt960301.0672 </DOCID>
<STORYID cat=a pri=u> A1897 </STORYID>
<SLUG fv=taf-z> BC-737-AIRCRASH-PROBE-NY </SLUG>
<DATE> <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">03-01</TIMEX> </DATE>
<NWORDS> 0700 </NWORDS>
<PREAMBLE>
BC-737-AIRCRASH-PROBE-NYT
RARE TESTING ON A 737 SEEKS ELUSIVE ANSWERS TO A CRASH
(bl)
By <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">MATTHEW L. WALD</ENAMEX>
c.<TIMEX TYPE="DATE">1996</TIMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">N.Y. Times News Service</ENAMEX> 
</PREAMBLE>
<TEXT>
<p>
   <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">WASHINGTON</ENAMEX>  &MD;  Air safety investigators have begun highly unusual
tests on a parked <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> 737, forcing parts askew with hydraulic
arms and clipping vital control cables in an effort to determine
why a sister plane owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">USAir</ENAMEX> fell out of the sky near
<ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Pittsburgh</ENAMEX> in <TIMEX TYPE="DATE">September 1994</TIMEX>.
<p>
   The investigation of that crash, which killed all 132 people on
board, is already the most extensive in the history of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National
Transportation Safety Board</ENAMEX>. And in a way it is the most worrisome,
because the 737 is the most popular jet in the sky.
<p>
   The board finds the cause of almost all crashes by looking at
the wreckage, the flight data recorders, radar records and similar
