 <TEXT><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paxar Corp.</ENAMEX> said it has acquired <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thermo-Print GmbH</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Lohn</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West Germany</ENAMEX>, a distributor of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Paxar</ENAMEX> products, for undisclosed terms. Shr 10 cts vs 32 cts Net 975,000 vs 3,145,000 Sales 159.1 mln vs 147.3 mln <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Key Tronic corp</ENAMEX> said it has received contracts to provide seven original equipment manufacturers with which it has not done business recently with over 300,000 computer keyboards for delivery within the next 12 months. The company said The new contracts represent an annual increase of approximately 25 pct in unit volume over last year. Canadian <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bashaw Leduc Oil and Gas Ltd</ENAMEX> said it agreed to merge with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Erskine Resources Ltd</ENAMEX>. Terms were not disclosed. Ownership of the combined company with 18.8 pct for the current shareholders of Canadian <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Bashaw</ENAMEX> and 81.2 pct to the current shareholders of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Erskine</ENAMEX>, the companies said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Entourage International Inc.</ENAMEX> said it had a first quarter loss of 104,357 dlrs, after incurring 70,000 dlrs in costs for an internal audit, a report for shareholders and proxy soliciation and 24,000 dlrs in startup expenses for opening <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX> offices. The company went public during 1986. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Entourage</ENAMEX> also said it has started marketing a solid perfume packaged in a lipstick tube called Amadeus, retailing at 15 dlrs. The company also said it has acquired <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">North Country Media Group</ENAMEX>, a video productions company. Shr 58 cts vs 29 cts Net 3,141,000 vs 1,440,000 Sales 24.7 mln vs 13.0 mln <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital Communications Associates Inc.</ENAMEX> said its board has named <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Ottinger</ENAMEX> president and chief operating officer. The company said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ottinger</ENAMEX> replaces <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bertil Nordin</ENAMEX> as president. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Nordin</ENAMEX> will become chairman and chief executive officer, Digital Communications added. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Teradyne Inc</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital Equipment Corp.</ENAMEX> signed a multi-license purchase agreement valed at over one mln dlrs for Teradynes Lasar Version Six Simulation System. The company said the agreement includes the option for futrue lasar purchases by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Digital</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Home Intensive Care Inc.</ENAMEX> said it has opened a Dialysis at Home office in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Philadelphia</ENAMEX>, its 12th nationwide. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bache Securities Inc.</ENAMEX>, 80 pct owned by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prudential Bache Securities Inc.</ENAMEX>, said it acquired its third <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toronto Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> seat for 301,000 Canadian dlrs. The company said the price was the highest yet paid for an exchange seat. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toronto Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> spokesman said an exchange seat last sold for 195,000 dlrs in March, which was acquired by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toronto Dominion Bank</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bache Securities</ENAMEX> said it needed a third exchange seat as part of an extensive plan to provide an enhanced level of service to clients. The seat will be used to further build its professional trading area, the investment dealer said. Qtly div 33 cts vs 28 cts prior Pay June 1 Record May 1 Roughly half of this years expected 130,000 hectare Dutch sugar beet crop is already in the ground, a spokesman for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Suiker Unie</ENAMEX>, the largest sugar processor in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX>, told <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX>. Conditions are generally good and the average sowing date for the crop is expected to be around April 11, against April 23 last year, and a 10-year average of April 14, the spokesman added. It is far too early yet to say what kind of output we can expect when it comes to harvest in September, but at least the crop is off to a very good start, he said. Last year, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Netherlands</ENAMEX> planted a record 137,600 hectares of sugar beet and produced a record 1.2 mln tonnes of white sugar, substantially more than the countrys combined A and B quota of 872,000 tonnes. This year, however, a self-imposed quota system has been introduced with the aim of cutting plantings to 130,000 hectares and reducing white sugar output to around 915,000 tonnes to minimise the amount of non-quota C sugar produced. Only farmers with a record of growing suger beet have been allotted quotas. This is expected to prevent the area being boosted by dairy or cereal farmers moving into sugar. Demand for shares in state-owned engine maker <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls Royce Plc</ENAMEX> is expected to be substantial when the government privatises it at the end of April, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Christopher Clark</ENAMEX> of the groups bankers <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Samuel Montagu and Sons Ltd</ENAMEX> said. He told a press conference after the release of an initial prospectus for the float that the issue would be offered to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> Institutions, company employees and the general public. As in previous flotations, clawback arrangements would be made if public subscriptions exceeded initial allocations. He declined to say how the shares would be allocated beyond saying that a significant proportion would go to institutions. A decision on what percentage would go to each sector would be made shortly before the sale price was announced on April 28. Minimum subscription would be for 400 shares with payment in two tranches, again a method broadly in line with previous privatisations. Chairman Sir <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Francis Tombs</ENAMEX> denied suggestions that <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls</ENAMEX> was a stock that should be left to the institutions. He noted that although the aircraft industry was cyclical, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls</ENAMEX> had several operations -- such as spare parts and military equipment -- that evened out the swings. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls</ENAMEX> 1986 research and development expenditure in 1986 was 255 mln stg and could be expected in the future to vary according to changes in turnover. He noted that net research and development expenditure was written off in the year it occurred, a policy that received inadequate recognition in one or two of the more extravagant forecasts of future profits. He made no forecast himself. In 1986, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Rolls</ENAMEX> reported that pretax profit rose 48 pct to 120 mln stg on turnover 12 pct higher at 1.8 billion. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NV Philips Gloeilampenfabrieken</ENAMEX> PGLO.AS shares are due to start trading on the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New York Stock Exchange</ENAMEX> on April 14, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philips</ENAMEX> chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Cor van der Klugt</ENAMEX> told the annual shareholders meeting. In March, the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Dutch</ENAMEX> electronics group announced it would end its current over the counter listing on the New York <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NASDAQ</ENAMEX> system and move to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">NYSE</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philips</ENAMEX> said the big board listing in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">New York</ENAMEX> is expected to boost its profile in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX>, Where 10 pct of all outstanding <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philips</ENAMEX> shares are held. The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">EC Commission</ENAMEX> confirmed it granted export licences for 118,350 tonnes of current series white sugar at a maximum export rebate of 46.496 European Currency Units (ECUs) per 100 kilos. Out of this, traders in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">France</ENAMEX> received 34,500 tonnes, in the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.K.</ENAMEX> 37,800, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West-Germany</ENAMEX> 20,000, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Belgium</ENAMEX> 18,500, in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Spain</ENAMEX> 5,800 and in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Denmark</ENAMEX> 1,750 tonnes. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pancontinental Oil Ltd</ENAMEX> said it arranged a 10 mln dlr private financing with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pemberton Houston Willoughby Bell Gouinlock Inc</ENAMEX>. The private placement consists of special warrants to purchase seven pct convertible redeemable preferred shares. The shares will be convertible for five years into common shares at five dlrs per share. The preferred shares are not redeemable for 2-1/2 years. Net proceeds will be used to increase working capital and finance exploration and development. Todays dollar convertible eurobond for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Realty Investment Trust</ENAMEX> has been increased to 100 mln dlrs from the initial 75 mln, lead manager <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Salomon Brothers International</ENAMEX> said. The coupon has been fixed at 5-1/4 pct compared with the indicated range of 5-1/4 to 5-1/2 pct. The conversion price has been fixed at 30-5/8 dlrs compared with last nights close in the U.S. Of 25-1/2 dlrs. This represents a premium of 20 pct. The put option after seven years was priced at 120 pct to give the investor a yield to the put of 7.53 pct. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Volkswagen AG</ENAMEX> VOWG.F, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VW</ENAMEX>, is due to make a formal announcement about its 1986 dividend tomorrow after saying the 1985 level of 10 marks per ordinary share would be held, despite massive losses because of a suspected foreign currency fraud. A spokesman said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VW</ENAMEX> s supervisory board will meet tomorrow to discuss the payout. A statement will be made afterwards. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VW</ENAMEX> has also said disclosed profits for 1986 will reach their 1985 level, despite provisions of a possible 480 mln marks linked to the currency affair. The figure is virtually the same as the 477 mln mark 1985 parent company net profit. When <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VW</ENAMEX> first confirmed the currency scandal on March 10 it said the management board would propose an unchanged 10-mark dividend to the supervisory board. A dividend of 11 marks would be proposed for the companys new preference shares. Share analysts said they saw supervisory board approval of the management board proposal as virtually a formality. Anything else would be more than a surprise, one said. Company sources said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">VW</ENAMEX> would have to dig into reserves to maintain the disclosed profit. Parent company reserves stood at around three billion marks at end-1985. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toronto Dominion Bank</ENAMEX>, Nassau Branch is issuing a 40 mln Australian dlr eurobond due May 15, 1990 paying 14-1/2 pct and priced at 101-3/8 pct, lead manager <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hambros Bank Ltd</ENAMEX> said. The non-callable bond is available in denominations of 1,000 Australian dlrs and will be listed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>. The selling concession is one pct, while management and underwriting combined will pay 1/2 pct. The payment date is May 15. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Toronto Dominion Bank</ENAMEX>, Nassau Branch is issuing a 40 mln Australian dlr eurobond due May 15, 1990 paying 14-1/2 pct and priced at 101-3/8 pct, lead manager <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hambros Bank Ltd</ENAMEX> said. The non-callable bond is available in denominations of 1,000 Australian dlrs and will be listed in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">London</ENAMEX>. The selling concession is one pct, while management and underwriting combined will pay 1/2 pct. The payment date is May 15. Shr 1.40 dlrs vs 1.16 dlrs Net 5,776,000 vs 4,429,000 Avg shrs 4,132,828 vs 3,834,117 <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Southmark Corp</ENAMEX> said it acquired 28 long-term care facilities containing for approximately 70 mln dlrs in cash. It said the facilities, which contain approximately 2,500 beds in seven western states, were bought from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Don Bybee and Associates</ENAMEX>, of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Salem</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Ore</ENAMEX>. The acquistion brings to 57 health care facilities acquired in the last three months, the company said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helen of Troy Corp</ENAMEX> said it filed with the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Securities and Exchange Commission</ENAMEX> a registration statement covering a 20 mln dlr issue of covertible subordinated debentures due 2007. Proceeds will be used for general corporate purposes, including possible repayment of bank debt, product development and possible acquisitions, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Helen of Troy</ENAMEX> said. The company named <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc</ENAMEX> as sole underwriter of the offering. shr 1.22 dlrs vs 1.28 dlrs net 226.4 mln vs 233.9 mln assets 80.45 billion vs 70.23 billion loans 35.16 billion vs 35.99 billion deposits 45.22 billion vs 39.68 billion return on assets 1.14 pct vs 1.35 pct return on common equity 18.20 pct vs 22.08 pct NOTE: 1987 qtr net was reduced by 20 mln dlrs because 1.3 billion dlrs of loans to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Brazil</ENAMEX> were placed on non-accrual. loan loss provision 35 mln dlrs vs 70 mln year earlier. Shr 74 cts vs 67 cts Net 8,067,000 vs 7,317,000 Qtr ends Feb 28 Shr Class A 61 cts vs 48 cts Shr Class B 59 cts vs 46 cts Net 2,358,000 vs 1,876,000 Revs 122,508,000 vs 105,871,000 Six mths Shr Class A 1.15 dlrs vs 86 cts Shr Class B 1.13 dlrs vs 84 cts Net 4,485,000 vs 3,378,000 Revs 242,453,000 vs 210,117,000 NOTE: qtr and six mths prior figures reflect two-for-one stock split in August 1986. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Hanover Insurance Co</ENAMEX> said its stockholders approved a two-for-one stock split. As a result of the split, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hanover</ENAMEX> said it increases the number of authorized shares of capital stock from 10.4 mln, having a par value of one dlr, to 20.9 mln, also having a par value of one dlr. The stock split is payable April 30 to stockholders of record April 10, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hanover</ENAMEX> said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Paperboard Co Inc</ENAMEX> said it has entered into an agreement with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ozaki Trading Co Ltd</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Osaka</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>, allowing <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ozaki</ENAMEX> to represent <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal Paperboards</ENAMEX> bleached paperboard sales in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Federal</ENAMEX> added it will be opening an office in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> in the near future. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Guardian Corp.</ENAMEX> said it has acquired a number of security services companies recently, with aggregate revenues of about 3,500,000 dlrs, for an aggregate cost of about 2,700,000 dlrs. It said it acquired guard service companies <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">C.S.C. Security Gaurd Service</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paramus</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cartel Security Consultants Inc.</ENAMEX>, the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Guard Services Division of Security Services of America</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wayne</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Capital Investigations and Protective Agency</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Hackensack</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>, and M <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Meyer Detective Agency Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">National Park</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX>. The company said it bought alarm service operations <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Certified Security Services Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Key West</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Fla.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Custom Security Services</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Myrtle Beach</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">S.C.</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">A-T-E Security Group Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Houston</ENAMEX> and the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Louisville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Kent</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Nashville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tenn</ENAMEX>, offices of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wells Fargo Alarm Services</ENAMEX>. Qtly distribution 7-1/2 cts vs 7-1/2 cts prior (excluding 2-1/2 cts special) Pay April 30 Record April 22 NOTE: Full name is <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Universal Medical Buildings L.P.</ENAMEX> The <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Zambian government</ENAMEX> has no immediate plans to follow last weeks increase in the producer price of maize with a hike in the retail price of maize meal, an official of the ruling party said. Last December, a 120 pct increase in the consumer price for refined maize meal, a Zambian staple, led to food riots in which at least 15 people died. That price increase, which President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kenneth Kaunda</ENAMEX> later revoked, followed pressure by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">International Monetary Fund</ENAMEX> ( <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMF</ENAMEX> ) to reduce the governments subsidy bill. However, if the producer price rise, from 6.10 dlrs to 8.67 dlrs per 90-kg bag, is not accompanied by a retail price increase, the government will have to spend more on subsidies, a practice discouraged by the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMF</ENAMEX>. There is no way out but to raise the subsidy levels of meal. It (the government) would have to choose between the demands of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">IMF</ENAMEX> and those of the people, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ministry of Agriculture</ENAMEX> economist said. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Blocker Energy corp</ENAMEX> said an offering of 20 mln common shares is underway at 2.625 dlrs per share through underwriters led by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Drexel Burnham Lambert Inc</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Alex. Brown and Sons Inc</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">ABSB</ENAMEX>. The company is offering 19.7 mln shares and shareholders the rest. Before the offering it had about 33.6 mln shares outstanding. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asarco Inc</ENAMEX> said it completed the sale of four mln shares of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Asarco</ENAMEX> common stock to an underwriting group led by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">First Boston Corp</ENAMEX>. The underwriters sold the shares to the public at a price of 22.50 dlrs a share, the minerals and energy company said. Proceeds of about 86 mln dlrs will be used to reduce outstanding debt, it said. The offering included 3.5 mln shares announced April 1 and 500,000 to cover overallotments. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Midland Corp</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Braodway Casinos Inc</ENAMEX> has entered into a letter of intent for a new company to be formed by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Carnival Cruise Lines Inc</ENAMEX> and Continental Hotel Cos to operate Broadways planned hotel/casino in the Marina area of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic City</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">N.J.</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Midland</ENAMEX> has agreed to spin off its 8.2 acre <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Atlantic City</ENAMEX> property to Broadway, a new company in which <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">American Midland</ENAMEX> shareholders would initially own an 85 pct interest. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wedgestone Realty Investors Trust</ENAMEX> said shareholkders have approved the acquisition of its advisor, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Wedgestone Advisory Corp</ENAMEX>, for 600,000 shares. It said completion is expected to take place April 10. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Sun Cos Sun Refining and Marketing Co</ENAMEX> subsidiary said it is decreasing the price it charges contract barge customers for heating oil in ny harbor by 0.50 cent a gallon, effective today. The 0.50 cent a gallon price reduction brings Suns heating oil contract barge price to 50 cts a gallon, the company said.Promising new findings in the use of a controversial experimental drug called Interleukin-2 as a cure for cancer will be published in the April 9 issue of the prestigious <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">New England Journal of Medicine</ENAMEX>, according to a <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wall Street</ENAMEX> analyst who has obtained an advance copy of the magazine. Among interleukins principal U.S. makers are <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cetus Corp</ENAMEX> CTUS, headquartered in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Emeryville</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Calif</ENAMEX>., and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Immunex Corp IMNX</ENAMEX>, based in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Seattle</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Wash</ENAMEX>. The journal, to be released late today, contains two articles reporting high remission rates several cancer types. The journal also contains a signed editorial concluding that the new results mark a significant milestone in the search for a successful immunotherapy for cancer. Interleukin-2, also known as IL-2, is a substance naturally produced by living cells in the laboratory. The drug is controversial because it was widely praised as a promising cancer treatment in early reports on its effectiveness in late 1985, only to come under criticism a year later for its failure to live up to its promise and due to its ravaging side effects. One of the new studies, conducted by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dr. William West</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Biotherapeutics Inc</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Franklin</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tenn</ENAMEX>., is particularly significant because it found far fewer harsh side effects after it changed the way in which the drug is administered. In that study, researchers administered IL-2 to 48 cancer patients and found a 50-pct remission rate for kidney cancers and a 50 pct remission rate for melanoma, a type of skin cancer, according to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Prudential-Bache Securities</ENAMEX> <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stuart Weisbrod</ENAMEX>, who obtained the advance copy of the magazine. For rectal and colon cancer, the researchers found no remissions, but none of the 48 patients treated had side effects serious enough to be placed under intensive hospital care, according to the article. In the second study, whose principal author is <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dr. Steven Rosenberg</ENAMEX> of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Cancer Institute</ENAMEX>, researchers administered IL-2 to 157 cancer patients and found a 33 pct remission rate in cancers of the kidney, a 27 pct rate in melanomas and a 15 pct rate in cancers of the colon and rectum. In the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">National Cancer Institute</ENAMEX> trials, a total of four patients died, the magazine reported, confirming the harshness of the drugs side effects as originally administered. Perhaps we are at the end of the beginning of the search for successful immunotherapy for cancer, said the editorial, signed by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Durant</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Philadelphias Chase Cancer Center</ENAMEX>. These observations reported by <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Rosenberg</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">West</ENAMEX> surely did not describe successful practical approaches ready for widespread applications in the therapy of cancer patients, the editorial said. On the other hand, if they reflect, as seems possible, a successful manipulation of the cellular immune system, then we may be near the end of our search for a meaningful direction in the immunuotherapy of cancer, the editorial concluded. </TEXT>