<TEXT>The largest U.S. textile maker focused on its own business as its competitors found merger partners, but now <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington Industries Inc.</ENAMEX> may have restructured itself into an attractive takeover candidate, analysts said. The takeover spotlight fell today on <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX>, which rose 4-7/8 to 52-7/8 on speculation that investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Asher Edelman</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion Textiles Inc.</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canada</ENAMEX> bought an almost five pct stake. A published report said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edelman</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion</ENAMEX> jointly acquired a stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX> and were weighing a takeover offer. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edelman</ENAMEX> would not comment, and a spokesman for Montreal-based <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion</ENAMEX> called the report just rumors. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX> said it did not know if the report was true. Wall Street professionals said they were not convinced of the story or that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edelman</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion</ENAMEX> would be the victors if <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX> actually came into play. Arbitragers said past comments from <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion</ENAMEX>, however, added credence to the speculation. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion</ENAMEX> has said that it was looking for a takeover in the U.S. Last year, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion</ENAMEX> unsuccessfully bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Avondale Mills</ENAMEX> and has maintained a 120 mln dlr line of credit to be used for a U.S. acquisition. A <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion</ENAMEX> spokesman said <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Canadas</ENAMEX> largest textile producer has been negotiating with many U.S. textile companies, but would not say whether <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX> was among them. There have been acquisitions in this area. Its not unusual that someone could be looking at <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX> after the housecleaning theyve done, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Eileen Gormley</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Thomson McKinnon</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX> sold its domestic operations, which made sheets and other linens, to <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">J.P. Stevens and Co Inc.</ENAMEX> for 110 mln dlrs last year. It also has reorganized management, and focused its operations on businesses that would be less affected by foreign competition, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gormley</ENAMEX> said. Theyve pulled back so as not to be a commodity marketer, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gormley</ENAMEX>. She said in moving more heavily into industrial fabrics, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX> bought <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">C.H. Masland</ENAMEX>, which supplies carpets and other fabric to the auto industry. In the past, they just spent and never realized the return on the outlays they did make, she said. You look at their record over the year, and I think theyre poised to be more profitable than they had been in the past, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gormley</ENAMEX> said. She estimated 1987 earnings of 2.50 dlrs per share, up from 2.01 dlrs per share. Some analysts today recommended clients not buy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX> at its current levels. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edward Johnson</ENAMEX> of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Johnson Redbook</ENAMEX> said he recommends selling. He said he believes the stock is worth only about 50 dlrs on a takeover basis and about 46 dlrs on an earnings basis. Some arbitragers, however, said takeover values have been placed on the company of 60 to 65 dlrs per share. After <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Ashers</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edelman</ENAMEX>) recent history, a lot of people dont find him very credible anymore, said one arbitrager. Another, however, said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edelman</ENAMEX> succeeds in forcing managements to take steps to enhance shareholder values even if he doesnt win the target company. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edelman</ENAMEX> was unsuccessful last year in offers for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Lucky Stores Inc.</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fruehauf Corp</ENAMEX>. He did succeed in buying <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ponderosa Inc</ENAMEX>. The stocks of other textile makers rose along with <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">J.P. Stevens</ENAMEX> STN climbed 5/8 to 44-7/8, and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fieldcrest Cannon Inc</ENAMEX> FLD, the result of a merger of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Fieldcrest</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Cannon</ENAMEX>, rose 1-1/8 to 39-3/4. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">West Point-Pepperell Inc</ENAMEX> WPM rose 1-7/8 to 67-1/8. </TEXT>