<TEXT>Senior Japanese officials tomorrow open talks with American trade negotiators in a last-ditch effort to avert new high <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> tariffs to be imposed on a wide variety of Japanese electronic exports. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Makoto Kuroda</ENAMEX>, vice minister of <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Japans Ministry of International Trade and Industry</ENAMEX> (<ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">MITI</ENAMEX>), is to hold two days of meetings with the Deputy <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Trade Representative</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michael Smith</ENAMEX>, and the Under Secretary of Commerce, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Bruce Smart</ENAMEX>. The new tariffs, to go into effect on April 17, are in retaliation for Japans failure to adhere to an agreement to end dumping semiconductors in world markets at below cost and to open its home market to <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> semiconductor shipments. They are to be imposed on goods which use semiconductors, including television and audio equipment and computers. Both <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> and Japanese officials have said there was little likelihood the talks would do anything to avert the 100 pct duties on 300 mln dlrs worth of Japanese shipments. President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX> announced the planned tariffs on March 27 after he said that close monitoring of the July 1986 U.S.-Japanese semiconductor pact convinced <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> officials that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> was not honoring the agreement. In making the annoucement, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX> said I am committed to the full enforcement of our trade agreements designed to provide American industry with free and fair trade. Trade analysts said his move was aimed as much at Japans semiconductor trade practices, which are said to have injured the <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> semiconductor industry, as Congress, which has complained about presidential timidity on trade issues. Congressional Democrats have pledged to enact aggressive trade laws to counter what they contend has been Reagans inaction to redress the growing <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> trade deficit, which last year reached 169.8 billion dlrs. About one-third of the deficit was with <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX>. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagan</ENAMEX> said there were recent signs <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Japan</ENAMEX> was beginning to adhere to the pact and that was why he was not terminating it. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kuroda</ENAMEX> said on leaving <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX> today he had no new proposals but did have an explanation of the semiconductor situation. He told the daily newspaper <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ashai Shimbun</ENAMEX> that <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Reagans</ENAMEX> decision was based on inaccurate data and an exaggerated sense of MITIs power to control Japanese traders. The <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">United States</ENAMEX> has excessive expectations, he said. To stabilize supply-demand relations which have been disrupted by excess inventories since 1985 will take some time. He also said that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">U.S.</ENAMEX> firms had not been aggressive enough in trying to sell in the Japanese market. </TEXT>