<TEXT>Top officials of leading industrial nations arrived at the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. Treasury</ENAMEX> main building to begin a meeting of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Group of Five</ENAMEX>. Officials seen arriving by Reuter correspondents included <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">West German</ENAMEX> Finance Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Gerhard Stoltenberg</ENAMEX> and <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Bundesbank</ENAMEX> President <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Karl Otto Poehl</ENAMEX>, French Finance Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Edouard Balladur</ENAMEX> and his central banker <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Jacques de Larosiere</ENAMEX>. Also seen arriving were Japanese Finance Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Kiichi Miyazawa</ENAMEX> and Japans central bank governor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Satoshi Sumita</ENAMEX> and British Chancellor of the Exchequer and central bank governor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Robin Leigh Pemberto</ENAMEX>. There was no immediate sign of Italian or Canadian officials. Monetary sources have said a fully blown meeting of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Group of Seven</ENAMEX> is expected to begin around 3 p.m. local time (1900 gmt) and last at least until 6 p.m. (2200 gmt), when a communique is expected to be issued. Italian sources said Italian acting Finance Minister <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Giovanni Goria</ENAMEX> met <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Treasury</ENAMEX> Secretary <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Baker</ENAMEX> last night. At those talks <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Baker</ENAMEX> apparently convinced <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Goria</ENAMEX>, who declined to attend the February meeting of the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Group of Seven</ENAMEX> in <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Paris</ENAMEX>, that <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Italy</ENAMEX> would participate fully in any meaningful decisions. <TEXT>