<TEXT> <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nantucket Industries Inc</ENAMEX> said <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">James Adams</ENAMEX> has been named president of its hosiery division, replacing <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">John Wineapple</ENAMEX>, and <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Terry Hampton</ENAMEX> has been named vice president of manufacturing for the division, replacing <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Howard Fromkin</ENAMEX>. No reason was given for the changes. </TEXT>