<TEXT>Faulty repair work by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">The Boeing Company</ENAMEX> BA.N was a contributary cause to a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Japan Air Lines Co Ltd</ENAMEX> JAPN.Y 747 crash on August 12, 1985, that killed 520 people, the final draft of a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ministry of Transport</ENAMEX> report says. There were only four survivors when the aircraft crashed into a mountain north of <ENAMEX TYPE="LOCATION">Tokyo</ENAMEX>. The report said inadequate inspection of the aircraft by Japanese inspectors after the repairs was another factor in the crash. The crew were cleared of any responsibility for the disaster. The report, which was sent on March 23 to the <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">U.S. National Transportation Safety Board</ENAMEX> for comment, should be released in late May. Under an international convention the draft must be submitted for final comments to the relevant authorities. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> spokesmen were unavailable for comment. On April 4, a <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> spokesman at the firms headquarters said the company would probably make no comment on the Japanese investigation teams report until it was officially released. On September 6, 1985, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Boeing</ENAMEX> said in a statement that the 1978 repairs it had undertaken were faulty. This statement did not, however, connect the faulty repairs with the cause of the crash. </TEXT>