<TEXT><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion Textile Inc</ENAMEX> considers a published report that it has bought a stake in <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington Industries Inc</ENAMEX> and is considering making a joint bid for the company to be a rumor, a company spokesman said. As far as I am concerned and the company is concerned, they are rumors and were not commenting on rumors, spokesman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Michel Dufour</ENAMEX> told <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Reuters</ENAMEX> in response to a query. All the information that has been given out publicly is that, yes, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion Textile</ENAMEX> is interested in making an acquisition that big...probably based on that people are starting all sorts of rumors, he said. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dufour</ENAMEX> said yes when asked whether the report was only a rumor, but said the company was not prepared to comment further. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion Textile</ENAMEX> president and chairman <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Thomas Bell</ENAMEX> was out of town and unavailable for comment. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion Textile</ENAMEX> last year made an unsuccesful 104-mln- U.S.-dlr bid for <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Avondale Mills</ENAMEX> and has maintained a 120-mln- U.S.-dlr line of credit to be used for an American acquisition. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Dufour</ENAMEX> said the company has been negotiating with many U.S. textile companies but would not say whether <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Burlington Industries</ENAMEX> was one of them. Burlingtons stock rose sharply this morning on the report, which said <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion Textile</ENAMEX> had joined with U.S. investor <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Asher Edelman</ENAMEX> to buy a stake in the company and to consider making a takeover offer. <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Dominion Textile</ENAMEX> , which reported operating profit of 11.1 mln Canadian dlrs last year on sales of 926.5 mln dlrs, has repeatedly said it will concentrate on expanding into the U.S. The company has said it plans to diversify into new product and market areas in addition to expanding its textile operations. </TEXT>