<TEXT><ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Ameribanc Inc.</ENAMEX> is raising 15 mln dlrs through an offering of convertible subordinated capital notes due 1995 with an eight pct coupon and par pricing, said lead manager <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stifel</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Nicolaus and Co Inc.</ENAMEX> The debentures are convertible into the companys common stock at 18.75 dlrs per share, representing a premium of 27.1 pct over the stock price when terms on the debt were set. The issue is non-callable for two years. It was not rated by <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Moodys Investors</ENAMEX> or <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Standard and Poors</ENAMEX> at the time of the pricing, <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Stifel</ENAMEX> said. <ENAMEX TYPE="PERSON">Burns</ENAMEX>, <ENAMEX TYPE="ORGANIZATION">Pauli and Co Inc.</ENAMEX> co-managed the deal. </TEXT>